<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Syneidēsilogia ̇or, The doctrine of conscience, framed according to the points of the catechisme, in the Book of Common-Prayer. / By the Right Reverend Father in God, John Prideaux, late Lord Bishop of Worcester, for the private use of his wife.</title>
            <author>Prideaux, John, 1578-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1697_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203209</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863253</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863253</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115443</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91004)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115443)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 211:E1697[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Syneidēsilogia ̇or, The doctrine of conscience, framed according to the points of the catechisme, in the Book of Common-Prayer. / By the Right Reverend Father in God, John Prideaux, late Lord Bishop of Worcester, for the private use of his wife.</title>
                  <author>Prideaux, John, 1578-1650.</author>
                  <author>N. Y.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 171, [9] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich: Marriot, and are to be sold at his shop in St Dunstans Church-yard Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's note "To the reader" signed: Y.N.</note>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 27.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conscience --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR, THE DOCTRINE OF CONSCIENCE, Framed according to the points of the CATECHISME, in the Book of COMMON-PRAYER. By the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>JOHN PRIDEAUX,</hi> Late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> for the private uſe of his Wife.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 3.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Holding the myſtery of Faith in a pure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>Major eſt honeſtatis fructus in conſcientiâ, quâm infama reponitur. <hi>Plinius ſecundus, in Epiſtolis.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich: Marriot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>St. Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi> Church-yard <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:2"/>
            <p>TO THE Right VVorſhipfull, M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> MARY PRIDEAUX, Relict of the Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father in God, JOHN, Late Lord Biſhop of <hi>WORCESTER.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His manuall (as the title of it tells thee) was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the private uſe of a moſt religious Matron: Yet ſuch is her love to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſhe deſireth not to confine it to her cloſet, for her owne inſtruction only; but freely permitteth it to walke abroad in the world, that others may partake of the ſame benefit with her. Indeed thoſe good women, we read of in the ſacred ſtory of the Gospell, we finde either Ministring to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or to his Members. <hi>Mary</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing his bleſſed head, and <hi>Dorcas</hi> making coats, and garments to cloth his ſervants. And ſo did that delicate Sex continue all the primitive time, and for many Centuries after, inſomuch that we finde <hi>Plac lla,</hi> the wiſe of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperor, deſcending from her throne to looke into the hoſpitalls, and into the
<pb facs="tcp:115443:4"/>Chambers of the ſick, and of thoſe in want, that ſo ſhe might be acquainted with, and ſerve their neceſsities. Then the love of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was hot, and did flame in the breaſts of profeſſors: But now that fire is decayed, and tis out of faſhion to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious. <hi>Devotion</hi> is termed Superſtition, <hi>Charity</hi> Popery, the <hi>divine</hi> grace of <hi>mercy</hi> in high diſgrace, even with thoſe that terme themſelves Saints, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and ſent into exile, <hi>to walke with God in the way of his holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> a legall faith, and <hi>faith,</hi> ſo ſtrangely exalted, that <hi>workes</hi> are tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled under foot, or rather buried in the grave of oblivion. Hence ſin becomes not only to receive kind entertainment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Sons of men, but is grown in ſuch requeſt, that ſhe hath patrons, and Advocates to defend, and plead her cauſe. Yea, we have thoſe that ſin with greedineſſe, becauſe they thinke they have ſuch an antidote, from the <hi>Spirit</hi> they pretend to, that all the poyſon thereof is not of power to do them injury. Herein not unlike the d ſciples of <hi>Marcus,</hi> a branch of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> that held forth (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> reports) that no ſin whatſoever, though of a crimſon dye, was forceable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to defile them, any more then the
<pb facs="tcp:115443:4"/>pureſt gold could be contaminated in a ſinke, or the glorious beames of the Sun ſuffer pollution in a dung-hill, and all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this pretenſe, and bottome, that they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by nature <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall.</hi> Tis not to reckon up the ſeverall diſtempers in this kind. Wherein we may complaine, with <hi>S.</hi> Jerom. <hi>Nunc lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentibus, &amp; pronuntiantibus plenus eſt orbis. Docent quae non didicerunt. Magiſtri ſunt, cum diſcipuli ante non fuerunt.</hi> The world doth now abound with thoſe that speake, and make a noiſe. They teach thoſe things they never learnt, from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor his Apoſtles. And the cauſe Of this evill is, becauſe ſuch take upon them to ſit in the Chaire of Divinity, and to give responſes from that Oracle, who never were educated in the <hi>Schooles of the Prophets,</hi> or ſate at the feet of a <hi>learned Gamaliel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prevent this <hi>ſpreading leproſie,</hi> it were to be wiſhed, that <hi>our Swords were beaten into plough-ſhares, and our Spears into pruning-hookes.</hi> I mean that the <hi>apple of diſcord,</hi> in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and Polemicall diſcourſes with thoſe of a differing perſwaſion to us in points of religion, might not be ſo ſtudiouſly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and treated with ſo much love, and
<pb facs="tcp:115443:5"/>kindneſſe as if that were the <hi>UNUM NECESSARIUM:</hi> whereby the Church of Chriſt hath been long rent, and torne into pieces, and to ſo little benefit of religion, that by advantage thereof, the <hi>Enemy,</hi> not whilſt we ſlept, but fought up to the ears in blood, concerning <hi>a trifle and a quiddity,</hi> hath ſowen his <hi>tare of high wickedneſſe, and profaneneſs even to Atheiſme.</hi> And if inſtead thereof, not only the <hi>Miniſters of religion,</hi> but thoſe <hi>over whom they have rule,</hi> would mind the end of <hi>our redemption,</hi> that <hi>we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delivered out of the hands of our enemies, might ſerve him in holineſſe, and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our lives.</hi> Luke <hi>1, 74.75.</hi> And in order thereunto, the firſt ſet upon the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and both upon the ſerious practiſe of a <hi>holy life.</hi> Our <hi>faith</hi> would then <hi>flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> and make a glorious ſhew with the <hi>fruit of obedience, and good workes:</hi> and with reaſon then it might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that <hi>righteouſneſſe, and peace ſhould kiſſe each other: and thereby</hi> too, we ſhould make appeare to the world, what <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſaid of old, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that our <hi>religion</hi> did not conſiſt in <hi>words,</hi> but <hi>workes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot
<pb facs="tcp:115443:5"/>only propoſing rules of holy living, but requiring in the profeſſors thereof obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereunto, which is likewiſe the ſenſe of our <hi>grand-maſter,</hi> and by him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in words not much different, Mat. <hi>7.21. Not every one that ſaith unto me Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father, which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Indeed action ought to be the life of a Chriſtian, and though <hi>ſpeculation</hi> may enrich his head, yet tis <hi>practiſe</hi> that makes <hi>his light to ſhine before men,</hi> whereby <hi>God is glorified,</hi> and <hi>religion reverenced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpoſe was this little treatiſe deſigned. That the Chriſtian man being freed from thoſe <hi>clogs,</hi> and <hi>ſcruples</hi> which hinder, and moleſt him in the way, might run his race in <hi>obedience,</hi> and a holy life with ſo much the more alicrity. We know, and are ſenſible what it is to have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>ſeared conſcience,</hi> which is not only an extreame <hi>brand,</hi> but an extreame <hi>evill.</hi> For that principle being ill affected, it doth infect the other parts with the malignity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whereby it hath a very bad influence upon the whole life of man, cauſing his actions to be very irregular. I ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:115443:6"/>need to illustrate this by examples. To cure this malady there is no remedy more proper, then to make it malleable by the power of Gods word, <hi>which is ſharper then any two-edged Sword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoule and Spirit, and of the joynts and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart.</hi> Hebr. <hi>4.12.</hi> And when that is done, by reſolving it in thoſe ſcruples with which ſhe is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, and winding her out of thoſe doubts, and intricacies in which ſhe is loſt, and ſhut up as in a Labyrinth. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this <hi>Reverend Praelate</hi> hath lent us his aſſiſting hand. A man of incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parts, both for his great learning and reading, as the world well knoweth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and other his learned workes doe abundantly teſtifie; yet, <hi>as tall a Cedar as he was,</hi> in this piece <hi>ſo humble, and condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> that he may be ſaid truely <hi>to have denied himſelfe,</hi> the points here handled being done without the leaſt oſtentation of quotations, and School-niceties: and againe with ſo much brevity, and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity, that they are made not only legible, but intelligible to the meaneſt capacity. Wherein he hath conformed himſelf to the practiſe, and example of that great <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb facs="tcp:115443:6"/>of the Gentiles,</hi> and Labourer in the Goſpell, <hi>S. Paul,</hi> who of himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, <hi>that he was made all things to all men, that by all meanes he might ſave ſome. 1</hi> Cor. <hi>9.22.</hi> a vertue, and happineſſe I confeſſe, as to be admired in our <hi>Worthy Biſhop,</hi> conſidering his great parts: So to be deſired in other learned men, who though they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved high renowne in the Church of God, yet have ſo locked themſelves up in abstruſe termes, or high rhetoricall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, that the benefit of their labours cannot deſcend unto the <hi>many.</hi> To avoid this rock therefore, the method he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth here is of the <hi>Catechiſme in the Liturgy,</hi> as being moſt plaine, and eaſie, and known to all; and which he alwayes very much extolled, as an <hi>excellent ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of religion,</hi> neither burthening the head with multiplicity of needleſſe points, nor leaving out any that was needfull. <hi>Milke</hi> indeed <hi>fit for babes,</hi> and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with great <hi>prudence</hi> by the compoſers thereof. Begun it was by him but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before his fatall ſickneſſe, by meanes whereof it wanted the happineſſe of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view, and ſome pages with this marke ['](neer the end of the book) were left empty, which are now adventured to be
<pb facs="tcp:115443:7"/>filled up, though by no learned hand, yet by one that had rather his low fortune and condition ſhould be taken notice of, <hi>in caſting but a mite into the treaſury,</hi> then an unwillingneſſe obſerved in him to ſerve his generation, according to the ſphear of his activity, Fare-well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Y. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115443:7"/>
            <head>Of Conſcience.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſcience is a faculty of the ſoul, <hi>ſitting as a Biſhop to overſee,</hi> &amp; cenſure all the actions of Man; with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall approving, diſlike, or doubting of them.</p>
            <p>That which we call <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in Inſenſibles, in Senſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <hi>Inſtinct,</hi> in Men vulgarly <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as it is applyed in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, may be called <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> which is nothing but Reaſon, freely acting with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality or ſeduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115443:8"/>
            <p>Hence it is ſet as a <hi>Judge, Iſa.</hi> 5.3. brought as a <hi>witneſſe, Rom.</hi> 2.11 retained as an <hi>advocate, Act.</hi> 23.1. called by ſome the <hi>dictate of reaſon, the Law of the underſtanding,</hi> that in reaſoning thus, playes the <hi>Logician,</hi> and makes an <hi>argument. A betrayer of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood is to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> this poſition is infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble out of <hi>Scripture.</hi> Then <hi>Judas</hi> brings in the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>but I have betrayed Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood;</hi> the concluſion will thereupon neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>therefore I am worthy to be condemned. Conſcience</hi> therefore (ſaith one) is the applying of our knowledge to particular acts, whoſe <hi>Court</hi> is the Heart, whoſe <hi>Proctor</hi> is Reaſon, whoſe <hi>Sentence</hi> is impartiall, if it be accompanied. <hi>with ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and godly ſincerity,</hi> as the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115443:8"/>Apoſtle ſets down. <hi>Our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing is this, the testimony of our Conſcience, that in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly wiſdome, but by the Grace of God we have had our converſation in the world,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12.</p>
            <p>For ſuch a <hi>conſcientious</hi> teacher, deſires to bee made manifeſt, not to the Eares alone, but to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of his hearers, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. and 5.11. So obedience to higher powers, is to be performed, not for comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or commodity, or feare of the penalty enſuing, diſobedience, but for <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> ſake, <hi>Rom,</hi> 13.5. For ſuch. <hi>Conſcience</hi> towards God, grief and ſuffering wrongfully is to be indured, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. For ſuch a <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> (as may appear in <hi>David</hi>) will be troubled, and ſtart
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115443:9"/>back at the offering violence, but to the skirt of the Royal robe of his <hi>Soveraign,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.5. And this <hi>Conſcience</hi> becomes one with that <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart,</hi> that maketh a chearfull countenance, and proves a continuall feaſt, when the cry goes otherwiſe abroad, <hi>the staffe of bread is broken, and they have no wine</hi> (as the wiſe man informeth us) a good conſcience feareth no colours; but a wounded conſcience who can bears?</p>
            <p>Thoſe that have taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the <hi>curing</hi> or <hi>ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of Conſciences in all variety of caſes, ſpend much time in diſcuſſing either <hi>grammatically,</hi> the originall, or meaning of the word, and how <hi>Syntereſis</hi> and <hi>Synidiſis</hi> differ, or naturally what place Conſcience ſhould hold, in reference to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115443:9"/>or will; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may be termed a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, or faculty, or an habit; what duties may be expected from it, what acts it perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, how liable it is to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightments, ſcruples, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murres, errors, woundings, cauterizings, extinguiſhings, of weakneſſe, and wayward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in good conſciences: of outragiouſneſſe or ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity in the bad, &amp;c. But a plainer path may ſerve our turne, who aime onely at <hi>practice,</hi> and leave diſputes to thoſe that have leiſure, or pleaſure to make uſe of them.</p>
            <p>This thing in no caſe may be omitted, eſpecially to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <hi>that as the ground is laid, ſo the building is like to prove firme, or tottering.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it will follow, that from doubtfull praemiſes in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115443:10"/>reaſoning, a warrantable concluſion may in no caſe be expected. In the Court therefore of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> theſe rules muſt ſtand as uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controleable. I. <hi>That mans Conſcience is known to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi> 1 Corinth. 2.10, 11. II. <hi>Therefore it can be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to none but to him, that can ſearch the depths, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the windings of it.</hi> III. <hi>Nothing by the ſame reaſon can binde or looſe it, but that which hath undoubted authority from God.</hi> IV. Thence it will follow, <hi>that the written Word of God muſt decide all our caſes of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, either by poſitive Texts, or clear deductions, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſtly excepted againſt.</hi> V. <hi>Traditions, Cuſtomes, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Lawes, Oaths, Promiſes, Vowes, or the like, may no further binde the Conſcience,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115443:10"/>then that they are conſonant, and backed by the Word of God.</hi> VI. <hi>No Indulgence, pardon or diſpenſation of Man can free, or binde the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but his onely that brings that key with him, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth, and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth, and no man open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi> VII. <hi>The Church and lawfull Ministers have the power of binding and looſing the Conſcience committed to them. Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23. which taketh effect in thoſe onely, who Religiouſly and with due preparation, are humble ſuiters for it, and with penitent hearts entertain it.</p>
            <p>The neglect of which <hi>rules,</hi> and foyſting in Decrees, and Decretalls, with Scholaſtical and Philoſophical determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, in ſtead of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and ſolid inferences from it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115443:11"/>hath entangled the antienter <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> with ſo many exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitances, that little good is to be gotten by them: and thoſe that ſet forth the ſame way, under the name of <hi>Morals,</hi> give rather a new <hi>dreſſe</hi> to the old Felt, then <hi>redreſſe</hi> any thing upon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grounds, as it will quickly appear, to thoſe that will come and ſee. Since the Reformation, thoſe that have recalled matter of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> to Scripture, not without great commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to themſelves, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in moſt things, to weak Conſciences, agree not concerning the method in delivering this doctrine: but this ſhould ſcruple no man, all laying ſure grounds, and driving to the ſame end, which the Apoſtle mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>The end of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115443:11"/>is Charity out of a pure Heart, and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and Faith unfeigned,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.5. This <hi>Three-fold cord</hi> may not be untwiſted and broken; howſoever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance be ſomewhat intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, <hi>without ſundring that which God hath joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The <hi>heart</hi> muſt be <hi>pure,</hi> without unclean or corrupt affections; the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience good,</hi> not tainted with by-reſpects, or vendible for any advantage; and <hi>Faith,</hi> the ground of all, muſt laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be <hi>unfeigned,</hi> not puffed up with preſumptuous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, but expreſſed in good workes, as the Apoſtle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. a tree, plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch rivers of water, will bring forth its fruit in due ſeaſon. And a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence faſtned by ſuch nailes, and pricked on by ſuch
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115443:12"/>Goads, will never ſhame the Maſters of the aſſemblies, for the diſpoſing that am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, they have received by the hand of one Sheep-herd and <hi>Biſhop</hi> of their Souls, to whom they have returned from the by-paths of mens traditions.</p>
            <p>As I cenſure not the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that any have taken in this kind: ſo I truſt none will take my diſpoſition amiſſe which I ſhall frame, as neer as I may, to the points of the Catechiſme in our Church-booke wherewith all ſhould be beſt acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The caſes of conſcience then ſo diſpoſed will come under theſe heads.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115443:12"/>
            <p>Concerning
<list>
                  <item>1. Religion.</item>
                  <item>2. Scripture.</item>
                  <item>3. The Apoſtles Creed.</item>
                  <item>4. The Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue or ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                  <item>5. Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                  <item>6. Sacraments.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking ſomewhat of all which (as God ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) obſerve, that <hi>C.</hi> ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for <hi>Conſcience</hi> propoſing ſcruples, <hi>D.</hi> a <hi>Doctrinal</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution or direction anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch queries by, 1. what, 2. whether, 3. why, 4. wherefore, briefly and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the caſe requireth.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115443:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of Caſes concerning Religion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHether Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion may not be thought to be a politique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the wiſeſt world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to keep the ſimpler ſort in awe, and order?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that Satan would buzze into buſie conceipts to make men atheiſts,<note place="margin">D.</note> that he might rule all: but herein he bewrayes himſelfe, for if by his ſenſible commerce <hi>Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28. Acts 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſeſſed, Pythoniſts,</hi> ſuch as have <hi>familiars,</hi> or <hi>ſpirits of divination,</hi> whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with, and worke by, doe apparant miſchief, it be made moſt apparent that there is a <hi>Devill,</hi> it will neceſſarily, thence be inferred alſo, that there is a <hi>God that puts a hook
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115443:13"/>into his Noſtrills,</hi> to reſtrain him from further miſchiefing this, inviſible frame of the world, with all the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof. Whom rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will further convince, that ſuch an ineſtimable piece of worke, as the world is ſeen to be, could not come to be ſo by chance of it ſelf, or indure as it doth, without a <hi>maker, and preſerver,</hi> which what may we imagine to be but <hi>God Almighty,</hi> to whom we owe our being, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving. Reaſon and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity therefore, will caſt us upon the acknowledgement of all Religious duties to be performed to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What aſſurance have Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that their Religon is to be preferred before that of the Jewes,<note place="margin">C. II.</note> Mahumetans and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtianity hath the moſt<note place="margin">D.</note>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115443:14"/>warrantable <hi>antiquities, and testimonies</hi> of all ages to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it, <hi>miracles</hi> beyond all exception, <hi>and prophecies</hi> of future contingencies, above humane comprehension to back it, ſuch <hi>doctrine</hi> as fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all men of all conditions, to live <hi>religiouſly</hi> in reſpect of God, <hi>juſtly</hi> in relation to others, and ſoberly in reflex upon their owne demeanure, with <hi>plaine instructions,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the originall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, and reward of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the onely freeing from it, the immortall rewards of another world, which the wiſdome of this world could never think of. This the Wiſeſt and Learnedſt in all ages have embraced, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and the Devils, with all their complices, have in vain oppoſed, the ableſt oppoſers of it, themſelves have been
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115443:14"/>convinced to juſtifie with <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Magicians, that the <hi>finger of God</hi> is in it. And none could take any excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt, which have not been anſwered to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. All which, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other <hi>excellencies,</hi> all other profeſſions are ſo farre defective that, upon ſlight examination, they will be found to be unreasonable, bruitiſh and ridiculous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May not all ſorts of people that never heard of,<note place="margin">C. III.</note> or were inſtructed in Chriſtianity, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine unto Salvation, if they live morally well in their own profeſsion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their puniſhment may be eaſier in another world,<note place="margin">D.</note> then that of thoſe who have lived amongſt them more diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, becauſe puniſhments are by Gods juſtice propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to demerits. <hi>Tire</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115443:15"/>
                  <hi>Sidon</hi> ſhall have an eaſier doom then <hi>Corazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> that were better <hi>inſtructed</hi> and did worſe. But <hi>for coming to the Father without the Son</hi> here,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.6.17.3. Act. 4.12. Ioh. 10.7.</note> or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, we can finde no way. No <hi>life eternall</hi> to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but by knowing him. <hi>No Salvation but by his name. No entrance but by that way, &amp; door.</hi> And this the Heathen doe in a manner confeſſe, when the beſt of their dead muſt be beholding to <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>'s boat, the <hi>Turkes,</hi> when they place their <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> they know not where, to ſupply them with all ſenſuall pleaſure, they had not ſo fully here. And what good can the <hi>Jewes</hi> howle for, in expectation of a <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> to ſave them in another world, beyond the date of all their Prophecies? who
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115443:15"/>tarrieth (no man knowes where) ſome, ſay lingreth at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seeing that they</hi> that turn many to righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">C. IV.</note> ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. and the King of Heaven would have men compelled to come in to the celebration of his Sons Marriage ſupper, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Whether thoſe of a contrary perſwaſion to Chriſtianity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our power, and living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us, may not be forced to conforme themſelves to our Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By no meanes.<note place="margin">D.</note> For the Commandement runs, <hi>goe and teach,</hi> not force <hi>by Fire or Faggot,</hi> or any other co-active wayes, <hi>all nations; Mat.</hi> 28.19. ſeconded by the Apoſtle, <hi>be infant, in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long-ſuffering
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115443:16"/>and doctrine.</hi> 2. Tim. 4.2. Religion being not to be planted or propagated in a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> manner by the Sword, but by the Word in an <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> manner, and method. <hi>I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by the mercies of God,</hi> Rom. 12.1. <hi>no lording over mens Conſciences,</hi> which St. <hi>Peter</hi> forbad long ago, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. (which his pretended ſucceſſors have little hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) whence the compulſion the Goſpel ſpeaks of, muſt be by <hi>perſwaſion</hi> not <hi>coaction,</hi> as appeares by the uſe of the ſame word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether Proteſtants by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Popery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. V.</note> 
                  <hi>may justly be charged to have ſet up a new Religion, differing from that which their anceſtors pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and are charitably thought to be ſaved in?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115443:16"/>
               <p>They can be charged no further with Novelties,<note place="margin">D.</note> then <hi>Joſias</hi> might be, and other Pious Kings, for plucking down Idolls, and purging Gods Worſhip from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; nor then our <hi>Saviour,</hi> for whipping out <hi>buyers</hi> and <hi>ſellers</hi> from the Temple. A religious Reformation, that ſeparates the <hi>pretious from the vile, the wheat from the chaffe, gold and ſilver from hey and ſtubble,</hi> rejecting the one, and reteining the other, hath been ever held neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and practiſed by thoſe themſelves, who blame it. Thus the Proteſtants have reteined the Creed, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, Lords Prayer, Baptiſme and Supper of the Lord, together with the ſame Word of God, which their anceſtors had. In theſe points conſiſt Religion, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115443:17"/>not in <hi>papall ſuperstructions,</hi> with which our anceſtors were deluded &amp; wronged. To turn therefore from a Papiſt to be a Proteſtant, is not to chang Religion, but to reject Superſtion, which, <hi>as a phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall leaven,</hi> had corrupted the whole Maſſe, and could not be tranſubſtantiated to any good, without ſuch a fair riddance, whereby we have left them no further, then they have left Gods Word: and are ready to comply with them againe in any thing, that thereby ſhall be convinced to be juſtifiable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Proteſtants truly urging,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. VI.</note> 
                  <hi>that a Papiſt may with a ſafe Conſcience be preſent at their Sermons, and Service, and communicate with them, in as much as nothing is conteined in them, but they themſelves have, and muſt allow of; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115443:17"/>on the other ſide may not a Proteſtant communicate with them in going to Maſſe, with the like liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 5.18.</note> Eliſha <hi>ſeeming to allow</hi> Naaman <hi>to be preſent at the Worſhiping the Idoll</hi> Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon?</p>
               <p>By no meanes.<note place="margin">D.</note> For that the preſence of a Proteſtant will not be permitted, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Divine Worſhip perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to a <hi>God of Bread,</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined to be made by five Latine words, pronounced by a Maſſe-Prieſt, which would make him guilty of more then Heatheniſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. To paſſe by <hi>Croſſe-Worſhip,</hi> and that exhibited to <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Reliques</hi> in their breviary. Neither hath the farewell of <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman, goe in peace,</hi> relation to his bowing down to <hi>Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> that he might joyne in<note place="margin">Ver. 17.</note>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115443:18"/>it, but to his religious pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, proteſting to ſacrifice to no other God but the Lord, and to afford no bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Rimmon,</hi> howſoever he ſhould, by his duty, be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to bow to his Maſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Rimmon.</hi> Others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Naamans</hi> petition to deſire only a pardon for that he had done, and thus read the Text: <hi>In this thing the Lord pardon thy ſervant, that when my Maſter hath gone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe of Rimmon, and worſhipped there, I have bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf with him, for which the Lord pardon me.</hi> To this the Prophet might well add, <hi>goe in peace;</hi> but the more warrantable interpretation is the former.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether entring into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery under the vowes of perpetuall Obedience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. VII.</note> 
                  <hi>Poverty and Chaſtity (as Popiſh Monks
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115443:18"/>and Nuns take them) be not rather a breach of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, or an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of Christian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, then a branch of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, to be termed ſo by an Excellency?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The anſwer is to be affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative,<note place="margin">D.</note> for although a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking to a ſcholaſtical, and a contemplative life under preſcribed rules, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accompliſhing of it, be not only laudable, but neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the training up of <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers to be ſent into the Lords Vineyard:</hi> yet the mewing of them up in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery for perpetuity, who ſhould be there onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained for a time, till they were fit to be imployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, (as they are in the Colleges of the Univerſities) and to bear the Church in hand, that by <hi>blind obedience,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115443:19"/>voluntary begging, and forced Chaſtity,</hi> men might <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogate,</hi> and over-doe the Scripture-Commandements to ſupply others defects, if ſuch ſpirituall redundancies be applyed by an wholſome indulgence. This is that will hardly give ſatisfaction to a well-grounded Conſcience, that pitcheth upon theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the rule, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deceive us.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.17.23. Gal. 5.1. Act 20</note> 
                  <hi>As God hath called every man, ſo let him walke, ye are bought with a price, be not made ſervants of men, it is better to give, then to receive.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115443:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Caſes concerning the Holy Scripture.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOw ſhall I be aſſured that the Scriptures we have,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. I.</note> 
                  <hi>is the Word of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By its (1.) <hi>Antiquity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note> (2.) <hi>Contents,</hi> (3.) <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Tradition.</hi> The <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the Old Teſtament (which carrieth the New with it in the ſame bottom) is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, in regard no Alphabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall writing can be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of equall ſtanding with it: for thoſe pieces fetched from the the Sons of <hi>Seth,</hi> the prophecy of <hi>Henoch,</hi> ſcraps fathered upon <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> or the like, might paſſe either by Tradition, or in Characters from hand to hand, the Alphabet being
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115443:20"/>too high an invention for mans contrivance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is worthily aſcribed to Gods firſt <hi>manuſcript of the Decalogue,</hi> upon the two Tables of Stone, in mount <hi>Horeb.</hi> Now as for the <hi>Contents</hi> of the whole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, they are ſuch both for matter, myſterie, and manner of expreſſion, that the greateſt wits of the world have admired it, that it hath born away the Bell, &amp; thoſe ſhamed themſelves, who have ventured to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it: though Satan and his brats hath maliced it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all writings whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which is a ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it came from God, whom he and his moſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. Laſtly, if <hi>Univerſall Tradition</hi> (wherein (if not all, yet) the moſt ſage and eminent judgements, in all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115443:20"/>ſucceeding ages have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred) ſhould not command an ingenious beliefe, we might queſtion every thing beyond the reach of our ſenſes, or make a doubt whether we had Grand-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or Parents, becauſe we knew them not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can that be received for a rule of Faith and Manners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. II.</note> 
                  <hi>which ſeems caſually to be written, without any ſenſible method or connexion, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction or direction, and in ſuch ambiguous termes, in points of greatest conſequence, that ſets at variance, rather then uniteth the most accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſearchers of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As God made man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note> 
                  <hi>though he ſought out many inventions,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.27. <hi>ſo the Law of the Lord is perfect,</hi> and ſure to <hi>enlighten the eyes,</hi> and make wiſe the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115443:21"/>ſimple, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19. but it is the <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant perverſeneſſe</hi> of men, <hi>that wreſt it to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. It is a blaſphemous cavil therefore, to ſleight the Scripture, as a caſual commonitor, againſt the expreſs texts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. <hi>Whatſoever things were written aforetime, were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning, that we through patience, and comfort of the Scripture, might have hope,</hi> Ro. 15.4. <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God &amp; is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in righteouſneſs that the man may be perfect, throughly furn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhed to every good work.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15.</note> To no other rules our Saviour ſends his oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers to be rectified, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. and calls the Diſciples tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing towards <hi>Emmaus, fooles,</hi> for being ſlack in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115443:21"/>them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. The method of which is not <hi>pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantical,</hi> as in Arts &amp; Sciences for lower matters, but <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> &amp; ſo divinely fitted, that all may be fit learners by it. Where, in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> in <hi>Joſuah, Iudges, Samuel,</hi> the <hi>Kings,</hi> &amp;c. follow the <hi>Law</hi> in the five books of it, to ſhew by <hi>examples,</hi> the rewards upon the fulfilling thereof, and <hi>puniſhments</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the breaking of it. The <hi>Moralities</hi> in <hi>Iob, David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> the exerciſe of patience, devotions, and all manner of wiſdome in all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whatſoever. The <hi>Prophets,</hi> beating down the wickedneſs of the times, lead us to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whom the <hi>Goſpels</hi> in the N. T. ſet forth as the <hi>Prophet, Prieſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>King,</hi> on which the Church muſt wholly depend, whoſe planting and progreſſe is ſet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115443:22"/>forth in the <hi>Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> doctrine laid down <hi>in the Epiſtles,</hi> and expectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> by a method ſo connected, that none but <hi>prating fooles</hi> (as the wiſe man termes ſuch) may carp at, wherein the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurities of ſome places are enlightned by the clearneſſe of others, or ſet as taskes for the induſtry of the greateſt wits, to beat down their pride and preſumption: that find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves over-maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they may ſeek unto God by prayer, for that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelves to come ſhort of. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the diſſentions that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, prove the faults of the <hi>wranglers,</hi> not the inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the rule, no more then the different judgments of <hi>Artiſts,</hi> doe the diſorder-lineſſe of the coeleſtiall, or terreſtrial bodies.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115443:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Upon canſideration of the new covenant fore-told by</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy,<note place="margin">C. III.</note> c. 31.33. <hi>and ratified by the Apoſtle to the</hi> Hebrews, c. 8.10. <hi>wherein a plain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is made of writing Gods Law ſo in mens hearts, that they ſhall not need to teach one another, becauſe all ſhall be ſo gifted; may not a weak Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be warped to think well of the</hi> Swenchfeldiſts, <hi>and enthuſiaſticall</hi> Wrigelians <hi>of theſe times, to lay aſide the</hi> letter, <hi>that the</hi> Spirit <hi>may act the more freely?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The old and new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant are both alike,<note place="margin">D.</note> under hand and ſeal, though the tenure be diverſe: the firſt was of Workes, the other is of Faith, for our Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the one ſaith, <hi>Doe this, and live;</hi> the other, <hi>Believe in him that hath ſatisfied for thee, and thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115443:23"/>The ſpirit indeed is promiſed to lead us into all truth, but not by frantick <hi>enthuſiaſmes,</hi> but by the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which is written for our learning, and many times walketh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of the <hi>Spirit</hi> too. <hi>God hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpoken unto us by his Son,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 1. Joh. 5.39. Rom. 1.16</note> which is his Word, and which alone ought to be our guide: <hi>ſearch ye the Scriptures</hi> is commanded us, which are the conduit of Life and Power of God unto Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thus we are taught of God, not to inquire at the <hi>Oracles</hi> of our Luſts, and Phantaſies, but of his <hi>word,</hi> not to be led by conceipts of our owne framing, but by the means of his preſcribing, the outward preaching of the Word, and the inward operation of the Spirit to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115443:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is thought amongst many Learned, Godly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. IV.</note> and painfull Miniſters, that the bare read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word in publick, or private, is not of power ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to beget Faith in the hearers; what comfort ſhall any therefore finde in aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies by ſcripture, where there is no preaching Miniſter? and how can I eſteem of that, my Conſcience tells me will doe me no good?</p>
               <p>Dilating upon a text of Scripture,<note place="margin">D.</note> taken at adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, muſt not be taken for the onely preaching, that begets Faith: it may ſet an. edge upon ſome hearers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; but can adde no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy to the Text, that is quick, and powerfull of it ſelfe, and <hi>ſharper then any two edged ſword,</hi> to diſcerne the very thoughts, and hearts intentions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. Beſide,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115443:24"/>it is well known that <hi>Moſes</hi> was held to be preached by the Apoſtle, in that he was read in the Synagogue every Sabboth day, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.21. Thoſe that benefit not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by hearing the <hi>Text</hi> read, which they may well rely upon, will hardly be better edified by the <hi>gloſſe,</hi> which may be as obſcure as that, and far more liable to exceptions. And ſhould not our Saviours, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>Sermons</hi> inſtruct them better, that often heare them reiterated with attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then a <hi>ſet ſpeech</hi> of a man of meaner gifts, that may be forgotten as ſoon as it is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and ofttimes is more intricate and obſcure, then the Text it indeavoured to explaine. This muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken not to detract from <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid,</hi> and <hi>ſeaſonable preaching,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115443:24"/>but for vindicating of the word read, from the abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſcorne too many put upon it, in theſe <hi>evill dayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scripture being acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be the undoubted word of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. V.</note> 
                  <hi>conteining that counſel of his, which he would have communicated unto all for their Salvation; with what. Conſcience may any portion of it be kept back from being read in the Congregation,</hi> as the Canticles, <hi>with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and moſt part of the</hi> Revelation <hi>in the New?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The not reading of ſome paſſages in Scripture, in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, detract nothing from their Authority, onely ſerve to put a difference between <hi>milke</hi> and <hi>ſtronger</hi> meat, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtomachs that are to receive it. <hi>I have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115443:25"/>many things to ſay unto you</hi> (ſaith Chriſt to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) <hi>but ye cannot bear them now.</hi> What would the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew titles, the <hi>Higgaions, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lahs, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms benefit the auditory? when the Teachers themſelves cannot agree what to thinke of them. So Genealogies in the <hi>Chronicles,</hi> and the not underſtood praedictions in the <hi>Apocalipſe,</hi> which the Learned make uſe of, the Vulgar may ſooner cavill at them, then in any ſort be bettered by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may any with a ſafe conſcience endure the reading of the,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. VI.</note> Apocrypha <hi>in the Church, eſpecially when ſo many Chapters of Canonicall Scripture are laid aſide, that may ſupply the yearly courſe of reading, with more ſure Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and more evident, then
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115443:25"/>from the</hi> Apocrypha <hi>can be expected?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the titles of our <hi>Bibles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note> the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> is ſufficiently diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall</hi> Scripture: ſo that the Chapters that are read out of it, are not preſcribed to ſet aſide the Canonicall; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left to the choice of the Miniſter, to reade ſuch Chapters in their ſtead, as he thinks fit. And by reaſon of the conſonancy of that which is read out of them with the Canon, the reſpect by the antient given unto them, and the inſtructive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſtyle, ſome choice paſſages are read out of them, as of <hi>ancient</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived homilies,</hi> making for the better explication of the Canon, which thoſe that moſt oppoſe them, cannot deny, but they may as well
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115443:26"/>be approved, as their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon a Text: which ('tis preſumed) they would not have to be taken as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How far may Scripture be conſcionably uſed in exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, in caſting out,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. VII.</note> 
                  <hi>or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Devills, or in charms for curing of diſeaſes, or in preſervatives, in wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it about us, to protect us from ſeverall dangers, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſuch caſes it may be uſed not at all;<note place="margin">D.</note> otherwiſe then as the ground of prayer, by which we muſt be ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants to God, that he would preſerve and deliver us from all evill. <hi>Naturall</hi> operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not to be expected from the words of Scripture, but <hi>morall</hi> from the ſenſe, and directions, no more then we can imagine, the leaves of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115443:26"/>a Phyſick book will cure a diſeaſe, or wound, if it be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the part ill affected. Thoſe pieces therefore of Scripture, or names of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Angels,</hi> thence pretended to be deduced by Exorciſts, and Magicians, or names of the <hi>three Kings of Cullen,</hi> or the beginning of <hi>Saint Iohns Goſpel,</hi> or the like, hung about the neck of any, are deluſions of Satan. <hi>The words that I ſpake unto you, are ſpirit and life</hi> (ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour) John 6.63. <hi>and were written that ye might believe, and that believing, ye might have life through his name, Iohn</hi> 20.31. not for charms to doe miſchiefe, or ſeeming cures upon the body, which Satan uſeth as a bait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſoule. Let the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoniſts</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi> ſay never ſo truly concerning S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115443:27"/>and <hi>Silas, theſe men are the ſervants of the moſt high God, which ſhew to us the way of Salvation, Act.</hi> 16.17. yet Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would not endure ſuch <hi>ſhe-Chaplains</hi> of the Devills ordering, who take up good to do miſchief, and act the Devils part in the attire of an Angell. The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the <hi>mongrell-bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemer, Lev.</hi> 24. ſhould make all conſcionable men afraid, how they adventure to make bold with Gods Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred name, or word, leſt perchance as the Sons of <hi>Sceva,</hi> they meet with ſome mad Devils, that will wound and ſtrip them for their folly; and terrifie others, cauſing them to burne ſuch damnable books of curious Arts, though of never ſo much eſteemed value, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.18, 19. On the contrary,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115443:27"/>a Conſcience muſt be made for the abuſing any parts of the Bible, or things once conſecrated to God to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and ſordid uſes, leſt <hi>Belſhazzers</hi> proſcription ſtand againſt them, to their ſodaine ruine, for <hi>non eſt tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ludere cum ſanctis</hi> (as the common ſaying is) it is not good to dally with a Deity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Caſes concerning the Apoſtles Creed.</head>
               <p>THree <hi>Creeds</hi> are received in all Catholick Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the firſt called the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> Creed, the ſecond the <hi>Nicene,</hi> and the third the Creed of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> The two latter of theſe are but expoſitions of the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> compoſed more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115443:28"/>to withſtand the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie, which denyed the Deity of Chriſt, and had then well-nigh over-ſpread the whole face of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Into the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> as our Liturgy hath hitherto led our fore-fathers, we were baptized. To make then this the firſt caſe of Conſcience, it may be well enquired,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the rejecting this Creed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. I.</note> 
                  <hi>out of our Liturgies and Catechiſmes, into which we were baptized, and to which our ſureties undertook for us, we ſhould alwayes ſtand to be, not a kind of renouncing, or rather plain Apoſtacy from the Faith we were baptized in, whereto may be applyed, that ſpeech of God to</hi> Samuel, they have not rejected thee but me?<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.7</note>
               </p>
               <p>They can beſt give ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115443:28"/>to this, that have been the actors in it. To ſay they ſupply it in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of their preaching, their auditors will tell them that they have not the art, nor are taught it by them, how to pick out ſo punctuall Articles for their Belief, and ſo to order them, that they may have them by heart, to be <hi>ready alwaies to give an account to every man that asketh a reaſon of the hope that is in them,</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> chargeth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. upon which they may ground the good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that followes in the next verſe. Now thoſe that have a touch of Conſcience, reaſon thus with themſelves, either the new Articles we are to expect from the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of our new Lights, are the ſame which we had in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115443:29"/>our old Creeds or different If they prove the ſame, why might not the old have ſtohd? but if we ſhall have new Articles of our Creed which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves hold to be above his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe authority to make) then woe to our anceſtors, that have ſo long miſled, and to our dull capacity, which cannot with a ſafe conſcience yet <hi>ceaſe to contend for the Faith,</hi> which hitherto we have conceived, <hi>was once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints,</hi> Jud. 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may the Conſcience be aſſured,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. II.</note> 
                  <hi>that this is the</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, <hi>which is ſtood ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much for, ſeeing the tradition, that it was made by the twelve Apostles, before their ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to preach the Goſpel, hath no warrant to confirme it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though it may not be call'd the Apoſtles Creed (as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers<note place="margin">D.</note>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115443:29"/>of the ancients would have it) becauſe it was made immediately by the Apoſtles themſelves; yet modern Divines are forced to agree in this, that the <hi>Articles</hi> in it are clear deductions from <hi>the Doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles:</hi> in which ſenſe it is rightly called the <hi>Apostles Creed,</hi> in <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> though not for <hi>compoſure.</hi> A true <hi>tranſlation</hi> is held with us for the Word of God, though not ſo <hi>immediately,</hi> yet as <hi>undoubtedly</hi> as the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt is ſaid in this Creed to be conceived by the Holy Ghost,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. III</note> 
                  <hi>according to that of Saint Matthew,</hi> that which is conceived in her is of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>cap.</hi> 1.20. <hi>and of Saint</hi> Lute, <hi>cap.</hi> 1.35. the Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the power of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115443:30"/>the higheſt ſhall overſhadow thee, therefore that Holy thing which ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God. <hi>Whence an ungroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Conſcience may gather, that Chriſt ſhould be rather called the Son of the perſon of the Holy Ghoſt; then the onely Son of the first perſon, the Father Almighty, which confoundeth the believed do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the ſacred Trinity, and is urged by Novelliſts to puzzle weake Conſciences?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> clears this,<note place="margin">D.</note> by putting a plain dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between <hi>begetting, made,</hi> and <hi>incarnate. Beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> hath relation onely to the Father, <hi>begotten of the Father</hi> (ſaith the Creed) not of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all worlds,</hi> that is, from eternity; <hi>as God of God, Light of Light, very God of very
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115443:30"/>God,</hi> being therefore of one ſubſtance with the Father that begot him, infinitely of a higher pitch then any thing that was made. For things made are all ſorts of Creatures, and ſo the Son, that begotten from eternity, was made Man in the fulneſs of time, when it is ſaid, he was <hi>incarnate by the Holy Ghost,</hi> and this incarnation is appropriated to the Holy Ghoſt, though it be the worke of the whole Trinity, united ever in all outward o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations; in regard this power of the Higheſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the Father and Son, and is next in order, and more conſpicuous to the producing of the greateſt effects. Whence, as in the Creation, the ſpirit of God is mentioned moving upon the waters, ſo in Chriſts
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115443:31"/>baptiſme, the Spirit is viſible in the ſhape of a Dove, and in inſpiring the Apoſtles, in cloven tongues, where the Father was onely heard, or heard of, not ſeen, and the Son not ſeen as the begotten Word, but as <hi>he took fleſh, and dwelt amongst us,</hi> Joh. 1. But theſe myſteries are more ſubmiſſively rather to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, then curiouſly pryed into. The beginning therefore of our Letanie, expreſſing as much in this behalfe, as any need learne, or profeſſe, of God the <hi>Father,</hi> God the Son <hi>Redeemer</hi> by taking mans nature upon him, God the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> proceeding from them both: which in a Trinity of perſons make but one God, to be mercifull to us miſerable ſinners, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme us further, when we ſhall come to ſee God, face
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115443:31"/>to face, <hi>not as now as it were in a glaſſe, but to know as we are known,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">C. IV.</note>
                  <hi>The Article of the</hi> deſcent of Chriſt into Hell <hi>is thought ſuppoſititious of ſome, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded at pleaſure by others, either for ſuffering helliſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonies in the Garden before his Paſsion, or for remaining in the ſtate of the dead after his buriall, untill he aroſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, or for his deſcent into</hi> Limbus Patrum, <hi>to fetch thence the fathers, or for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending into the place of the damned, to proclaime his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for ſin, and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing over Death and Hell,</hi> of which it was not poſſible he ſhould be holden, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Among all which diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, where is it ſafe for a ſcrupulous Conſcience to rely, and quiet it ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note>On the generall believing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115443:32"/>of the thing, as it is laid downe out of this, and the <hi>Athanaſian Creed,</hi> in the third Article of our Church, in theſe words, <hi>As Chriſt died for us, ſo it is to be believed, that he went down into Hell:</hi> and not further to trouble our ſelves about the preciſe manner of it, which, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly not revealed in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, intangleth rather the curious ſearchers, then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords ſatisfaction for the conſcience. If then from the conſideration of this one more evident place, <hi>Col,</hi> 2.15. <hi>Chriſt blotting out the hand writing of Ordinances that was against us, which was contrary to us, and took it out of the way by nailing it to the Croſſe, ſpoiled upon it prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, and made a ſhew of them openly, triumphing over them in it,</hi> we collect
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115443:32"/>that after his going in the Garden, through wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, which he had undertaken, and Sufferings on the Croſſe by Satans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, upon the <hi>conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum eſt,</hi> or finiſhing the worke of our Redemption, his Soul encountred Satan in a ſpirituall way (who found nothing to except a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and therefore was conquered and triumphed over) with his complices, with <hi>O Death where is thy sting, O Grave where it thy victory?</hi> We may well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this Article, as having the like ground with the reſt, and to continue to ſing in the <hi>Te Deum, when thou hadſt overcome the ſharpneſſe of Death</hi> (which was done by the deſcending, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing over all helliſh forces) <hi>thou didst open the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115443:33"/>Kingdome of Heaven to all believers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Upon the Article concerning</hi> the Catholick Church,<note place="margin">C. V.</note> 
                  <hi>the weaker Conſciences, by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh emiſſaries, are thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared; out of the Catholick Church there can be no Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as all ſides grant up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that in the Act.</hi> 2.47. And the Lord added to the Church, ſuch as ſhould be ſaved: <hi>but the Roman Church is onely the Catholick Church, therefore whoſoever will be ſaved, before all things, muſt firſt turn Roman Catholick?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This grand impoſture in depraving the Article of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,<note place="margin">D.</note> wherein the Saints community, and forgiveneſs of ſinnes conſiſteth, is (as a Spiders web ſet up to catch Flies) thus ſwept off. Acknowledging that out of the Catholick Church, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115443:33"/>is not to be expected, it will be denyed in the next place that <hi>Rome</hi> is the only Catholick Church, and made evident that it is only a particular member of it, as the Churches of <hi>Corinth, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia, Epheſus</hi> and the reſt were, when S. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Romans.</hi> Theſe were not then <hi>members</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>ſiſters</hi> with it, not <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> with it. To omit Logick quiddities in diſcovering the fallacy, what a piece of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning is this; becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> is Catholick, therefore the Church of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> cannot be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick; as much as to ſay your nag ambleth, mine may not, or muſt doe it in ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to yours, and yet the Catholick Church is, the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115443:34"/>Creed, is not made by us an imaginary idea, as ſome put upon us, but a generall that includs many particulars un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, as the generall notion. of a City doth this or that City, to which it doth equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impart the name, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where the particular is the object of ſenſe, and ſet on an hill cannot be hid, but the generall the object of faith, which is of things under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, or to be believed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Article of the</hi> forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes,<note place="margin">C. VI.</note> 
                  <hi>may much trouble a weak conſcience, in that we read the ſin againſt the Holy ghoſt ſhall never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given; beſide there are ſins which waſte the conſcience, and deſtroy it, that admit of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſurmount the abſolution of the Miniſter of the Goſpell, which is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to worke by prayer, not
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115443:34"/>power, what peace then may be had, or pacification in ſuch diſtraction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which Gods word holdeth forth unto us, Firſt,<note place="margin">D.</note> this ground muſt be laid that forgiveneſſe cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected without repentance, <hi>except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh,</hi> Luke 13.3. Then that the ſin againſt the Holy ghoſt may be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by two ſorts of people. Firſt, by ſuch as being unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, by reaſon, of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, and condition, have the word ſo evidently laid home to their capacities, that their conſciences are convinced that they heare the right; and yet for by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of pleaſure, pelf, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, or the like, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and maliciouſly ſet themſelves againſt the light of it; and prefer darkneſſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115443:35"/>before it. This was the courſe of the Phariſees, who were convinced ſufficiently, that our Saviours caſting out of divells, could not be but by the over-maſtering, divine power (<hi>as Nicodemus ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acknowledged, we know that thou art a teacher come from God, for no man can doe thoſe miracles which thou doeſt, except God be with him,</hi> Jo. 3.2.) yet they malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly gaine-ſaid it, and bore the people in hand, that <hi>it was by Beelzebub the Prince ef the devills,</hi> Matth. 12. By a ſecond ſort the ſin againſt the Holy ghoſt is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that have liſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Church, <hi>taſted of the heavenly gift,</hi> and word of God, yet then wilfully fall away, and renounce Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. and 10.26. neither of theſe can be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115443:35"/>by repentance, becauſe the forgiveneſſe of ſins is only to be had in the pale of the Church, and thoſe ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> the firſt ſort, refuſe to enter, and the ſecond out themſelves from the ſafe condition they were in; the firſt are termed <hi>blaſphemers,</hi> the other <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> whoſe caſe is far different from the greateſt offender, who remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſtill in the Church, whereby repentance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins may be had, though never ſo much cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for vengeance, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the conſcience. <hi>Though your ſins are as Scarlet, I will make them as white as ſnow; though they be red like crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they ſhall be as wool,</hi> Iſai. 1.18. <hi>Come unto me, take my yoke,</hi> though ſeven, nay, though legions of devils poſſeſſe you, <hi>I will give you
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115443:36"/>reſt,</hi> Matth. 11.28. When the Miniſtery of abſolution, and abſolution of a lawfull Miniſter is to be accounted more then petitory, which may be performed by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pious friend, but not au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatively (as it is ſaid) and by way of power. For as a Judge who hath a lawfull commiſſion from his ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, that can grant it, may abſolve or condemn a party brought before him, which another man, perchance of more eminency, may not doe; for want of a calling to it: ſo a Miniſter by vertue of his commiſſion given him, <hi>whoſe ſins ye remit, they are remitted unto them, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoevers ſins ye retaine, they are retained,</hi> Jo. 20.23. Matth. 18.18. provided alwayes that they goe not beyond the limits of their commiſſion,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115443:36"/>which conſidered, as it ſhould be, by tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, would mould them to a greater regard of their ſpirituall guides, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, which now are ſo caſt aſide by thoſe, who know not, or care not, what in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they are moſt to look after.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How can that Creed be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſymbole of our Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. VII.</note> 
                  <hi>which leaves out the chiefe of all, that</hi> Faith only juſtifieth; <hi>and hath nothing concerning</hi> Predeſtination, <hi>or Mans</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of will, <hi>concerning which ſo many conſciences are, and have been troubled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt Scruple is cleared by the firſt word of the Creed, <hi>I beleeve.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note> Wherein the word <hi>Beleeve,</hi> being the proper act of Faith, ſheweth that Faith is laid for the Ground, that all the Articles
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115443:37"/>that follow, ſtand upon; and <hi>I,</hi> the firſt ſyllable, requireth an application of every arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to our ſelves. So that in this ſenſe they are to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: <hi>I beleeve in God,</hi> that he created mee, as all other creatures beſides, and <hi>in Ieſus Christ,</hi> not onely that hee is <hi>his onely ſon, conceived by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the Virgin Mary,</hi> but that he <hi>Suffered, was crucified, dead and buried,</hi> triumphed over death, and hell, and <hi>roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine</hi> for my juſtification. By whoſe ſatisfaction I am quitted, and delivered from the bondage of ſin, Satan, &amp; the Law, to ſerve him in <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> to God, and <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> towards my neighbour, all the dayes of my life. And is not here the doctrine that faith juſtifieth alone, not a temporall, hiſtoricall, or
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115443:37"/>ſpeculative habit; but an affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and reliance on that which Chriſt hath done for me, without which as it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe God, ſo it is impoſſible likewiſe to caſe a troubled conſcience. The ſecond ſcruple of Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation may be taken off, by a ſober conſideration of the attributes of <hi>Almighty,</hi> and creating all things aſcribed to God, which includeth the other attributes. For he that made all things of nothing, and may diſpoſe of his owne as he pleaſeth, may chooſe, or paſſe by whom hee liſteth. But herein, what hee hath done from eternity, hee acquaints us not with: but leaves us to be guided, to thinke, or doe as his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word, and certain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions from thence lead us. Vnder which moſt free
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115443:38"/>diſpoſition of the Almighty, Mans freedome given, loſt, and reſtored, muſt be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be placed : for <hi>it is he that worketh in us to will and to doe of his good pleaſure, Philip.</hi> 2. In like manner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary points to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation may be reduced, and thoſe that cannot, may not bee impoſed upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience as neceſſary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115443:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Caſes concerning the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, or Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</head>
               <p>COncerning the <hi>Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> or Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, theſe points are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt: (1.) That theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements were written with the finger of God on two Tables of Stone:<note place="margin">Exod. 31.18.32.16.</note> (2.) That they were written on both ſides: (3.) That theſe Tables being broken by <hi>Moſes</hi> at the ſight of the <hi>Idoll-calfe,</hi> they were written againe by God in the ſame words, they had at firſt, but upon two Tables of ſtone of <hi>Moſes</hi> hewing:<note place="margin">34.</note> (4.) That they were juſt ten in number: (5.) That our Saviour reduceth all the duties of them to two
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115443:39"/>heads, the <hi>love</hi> due to <hi>God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 22.37. Luk. 10.27.</note> and <hi>the love</hi> to bee perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>to our neighbour:</hi> (6.) That moſt of the Ancient deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned three of theſe Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements to the firſt Table (which diviſion thereupon is by moſt Churches reteined) and ſeven to the ſecond. Notwithſtanding divers of the Reformed aſcribe foure to the firſt, and ſix to the ſecond Table. But ſuch differences, in things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, have been alwayes tolerated amongſt ſober men without prejudice to any diſſenting. I ſhould thinke the diviſion of the <hi>Jewes</hi> to be more equall, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable; that five Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements ſhould belong to the firſt Table, to ſhew our duty towards God: and ſo many to the ſecond, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing our duty towards
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115443:39"/>our neighbour, both having a like number to inſtruct our chriſtian Carriage to God, and Superiors, in the firſt: and to our neighbours, and inferiors, in the latter. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the firſt, theſe caſes ſeem to be of moſt uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Saviour having made full ſaiisfaction, and quitted us from Gods wrath, the curſe of the Law, and the intereſt of Satan, what need any works, or duties to be performed on our parts, or paying that debt againe by obſerving the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath ſo confeſſedly diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; Is not the conſcience hence leſt at liberty to do what ſhe listeth, and the opinions of moderne</hi> Antinomians <hi>(as they are called) juſtified, who urge that the commandements are by the Goſpell cancelled?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note>The law delivered by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115443:40"/>was <hi>ceremoniall, judiciall, and moral.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> propoſed types, and ſhadowes, which vaniſhed at the comming of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> which was the ſubſtance. The <hi>ſecond</hi> ſort had relation to the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh common-wealth, with which it did expire, and had its period. So that the <hi>morall</hi> Law in the ten commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments come only in this point in queſtion, that is in plaine termes, ſeeing we, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtified by faith only, in believing and depending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that which Chriſt hath done for us, may doe as we liſt; for keeping or not kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the commandements can do us neither good nor harm. The ſetling of the conſcience herein is, (1.) the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing betwixt <hi>juſtification,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sanctification,</hi> then (2.) by conſidering what that <hi>faith is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115443:40"/>that justifieth,</hi> (3.) by weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meanes whereby we ſhall come to that happineſſe and eternall ſalvation, which faith hath ſet us free to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. <hi>Faith</hi> indeed only on our part juſtifieth us before Gods tribunall, by pleading that our Saviour hath paid that debt for us, which we could not doe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould not in juſtice be exacted againe. And this is that, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much urgeth, in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and elſewhere. But as to the <hi>ſecond</hi> point, S. <hi>James</hi> will purpoſely tell that this <hi>juſtifying faith</hi> muſt not be meerly <hi>ſpeculative,</hi> but <hi>operative,</hi> expreſſed in good workes, as the Apoſtle enjoyneth us, which hath <hi>charity</hi> annexed to it, that without it, it is <hi>dead</hi> and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall, rather damning
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115443:41"/>then ſaving. Whereupon our <hi>Saviour</hi> calleth upon us, <hi>if you love me</hi> (for that I have freed you) keep <hi>my comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi> and in a more ſtrict manner then was urged, and practiſed by the Scribes and Phariſees. And S. <hi>Pauls</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is peremptory (to ſhew the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> he writ to the faith <hi>included,</hi> not <hi>excluded</hi> good works) <hi>follow peace, and holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord, Heb.</hi> 22.14. All then of any judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment grant that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> muſt be neceſſarily joyned; but whether <hi>Works</hi> come in as neceſſary fruits of faith, or co-partners with it in juſtification, this breeds the quarrel: And ſome have gone ſo far, as to make Faith nothing elſe but obedience to the Commandements. But no conſcience ſhould dare to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115443:41"/>appeare with works to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie it before Gods Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, but only thoſe of our Saviour which the Prince of this world could not except againſt. As our faith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Chriſt juſtifieth us, ſo our workes muſt juſtifie, or make good our faith. <hi>We are delivered from the hands of our enemies</hi> (ſaith old <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>) <hi>to ſerve God without fear,</hi> but how? in ſerving him <hi>in holineſſe,</hi> as to God-wards, <hi>and righteouſneſſe,</hi> towards our neighbour, <hi>before him all the dayes of our lives.</hi> Luk. 1.74, 75.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">C. II.</note>The ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>forbids not only all kind or idolatrous worſhip, but the preciſe making of any ſort of images, pictures , ſtatues, graven, molten, of Stone, Braſſe, or other mettall, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars erected or the like, with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115443:42"/>what conſcience then may images be permited to remain in Churches, where a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of idolatry is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note>The Commandement for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids not the making, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of images in any places abſolutely, but onely for a religious uſe; falling downe to, at or before them by way of adoration, as they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the true object of our worſhip. For as the <hi>firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement</hi> holdeth us to the true worſhiping of the living God, that only knowes the heart, and can diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene right meaning and hypocriſie: ſo the <hi>ſecond</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the due manner he would be worſhiped in, not by images, or <hi>imaginations,</hi> or Chimeras, the calves of man, or poeticall inventions, but <hi>in the beauty of holineſſe,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115443:42"/>in ſpirit and in truth,</hi> as he hath appointed. Images then not of God, who is infinite, and muſt not be confined to the idea of a peeviſh painter, may be tolerated, or made (1.) for <hi>historicall uſe,</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative, or memoriall, as the ſtructure of the arke, temple, and holy utenſills belonging to it, and the boundaries of places, and Countries by mapps, which our beſt bibles have. (2.) They may ſerve for <hi>orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as the cherubims, and palme-trees preſcribed by God himſelfe in Sacred ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes. (3.) By way of <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes,</hi> expreſſing ſage para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and paſſages as make for inſtruction in faith, and manners. As the parable of the <hi>rich glutton,</hi> and <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> the <hi>Prodigall,</hi> or the like. But upon theſe pretences to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115443:43"/>be taken in by a new title of <hi>relative worſhip,</hi> and ſo to be crouched unto, kiſſed, and clothed, alſo to be perfumed and prayed at, this is that which is ever to be proteſted againſt, and deteſted. Our memorialls, directions, and praeſcriptions for Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are ſet before us, (1.) in his <hi>workes,</hi> (2.) in his <hi>word,</hi> (3.) in his <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God. The word of the Lord gives wiſdome unto the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Images are teachers of lyes, in this behalfe. And for remembring the gracious worke of our <hi>redemption,</hi> the direction runneth not, get thee a material crucifix, or an artificiall picture of it, to ſtir up thy devotion: but take <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> break it, and drink it, according to thy Saviours ſolemn inſtitution.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115443:43"/>
                  <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me.</hi> People amongſt us are now ſo weaned from theſe babies, that they are left in divers Churches, without looking after: But if they chance to prove ſcandalous, the removall of them, as of the brazen ſerpent, in a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full way, hath been alwayes thought, &amp; taught amongſt us to be neceſſary and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the</hi> third Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>may be referred,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. III.</note> 
                  <hi>the</hi> taking of Gods name in vain (1.) <hi>by irreverent uſing of it in common talke, or merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (2.) <hi>In not profeſsing, and confeſsing of our Faith upon juſt occaſion,</hi> (3.) <hi>uſing aſſeverations, obtestations, or proteſtations to deceive,</hi> (4.) <hi>in imprecations,</hi> (5.) <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> (6.) <hi>gallanting it in Oathes, and Perjury,</hi> (7.)
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115443:44"/>
                  <hi>with the leaſt, or no conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all of the Penalty that lyes upon it,</hi> The Lord wil not hold him guiltleſſe, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeth his name in vain: <hi>In all which, theſe caſes ſhould eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally be looked after. Whether</hi> (1.) <hi>ignorance,</hi> (2.) <hi>paſsion,</hi> (3.) <hi>aequivocation,</hi> (4.) <hi>fraud,</hi> (5.) <hi>force,</hi> (6.) <hi>a good intention,</hi> (7.) <hi>the avoidance of utter ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine may excuſe from Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note>For directing the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence herein, it muſt be firſt taken for a ground: That <hi>an Oath is a Religious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and neceſſary confirmation</hi> (becauſe not otherwiſe to be uſed, but in caſes of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity) <hi>of things doubtfull, by calling on God, to be a witneſs of our true meaning, to end differences, and a revenger of falſhood, if we ſwear falſly; wherein the failing is Perjury,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115443:44"/>not to pardoned but by God himſelfe, who in the higheſt degree is diſmoured by it.</hi> Secondly, <hi>ſuch an Oath</hi> (to paſſe by other diſtinctions) is either <hi>aſſertory,</hi> or promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory. The aſſertory is that which uſually is miniſtred to, and taken by witneſſes for the affirming, or deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a thing paſt; wherein the Perjury is apparent, and inexcuſable, if the truth prove otherwiſe, then the Oath hath aſſerted it to be. The <hi>promiſſory</hi> is an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for performance, or forbearance ſomewhat to come, taking God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that that is truly meant, which is ſworne. This (as much leſſe in the aſſertory Oath for things paſt) ignorance cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, for why wilt thou ſweare that which thou art
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115443:45"/>incertaine of? Neither ſhould paſſion, as fury, fear, love, hatred, or the like. For theſe overbearing Religion, rather aggravate then extenuate the fault, which the yeilding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, where it ſhould not, maketh voluntary. And herein <hi>equivocation</hi> is ſuch a deluding of God, and Man, that it makes it to be of a deeper tincture, and leſſe tolerable, then more open fraud, whereby though we cozen Men, <hi>God will not be mocked.</hi> A good intention, and the avoidance of utter ruine, may put one for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn into a capacity of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in regard of humane frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but not of pardon for Perjury, when the gaine of the whole world may not countervaile the loſſe of a Soule.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">C. IV.</note>
                  <hi>Whether an oath taken by a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115443:45"/>party that is in a capacity to ſweare, wherein God is called on to be a witneſse, in expreſſe, or incluſive termes, may be diſpenſed with by any created power, or authority, from the disburdening of a tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſingle anſwer cannot ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie a queſtion, conſiſting of many diſtinct particulars, yet this may paſſe for a rule in ſome ſort generall, That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very oath, upon what motive ſoever taken, bindeth the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker to the poſſible perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it, if the thing be good: or to a ſerious repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for perjured raſhnes, if it be found otherwiſe. In particular, (1.) an oath is to be diſtinguiſhed from a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aſſeveration, promiſe, vow, proteſtation, or engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; wherein God is not called to arbitrate, but Man
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115443:46"/>ſtandeth upon his owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and ſincere deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or true meaning: and therefore the breach of theſe is accounted rather <hi>diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty,</hi> then rude <hi>perjury.</hi> Where, (2.) notice is to be taken, that the party ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, be not uncapable, by reaſon of infancy, madneſſe, or diſtemper, to take an Oath: for the actions of ſuch come not under the cenſure of the <hi>Court of Conſcience.</hi> (3.) ſuch uſual forms of ſpeech as theſe, <hi>God is my judge, God knowes I meant no harme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God I had no ſuch thought,</hi> or the like, muſt be reckoned as Oathes; whereas <hi>by my Faith or Troth, or of my Soul, or Honesty, or Salvation,</hi> or the like, be but ſerious aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verations: of reſpecting which religiouſly, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience muſt bee made.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115443:46"/>Whence that <hi>Amen, Amen,</hi> verily, verily, muſt not be accounted an Oath of him, that gave in charge, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon converſation, not to ſwear at all. (4.) Beſides here, <hi>the ſwearing by Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> is no way approved by a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and diſcovers the heedleſſe vanity of a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> worthy to be puniſhed, though not for Perjury, yet for peeviſh profaneſſe. As <hi>by the Heavens, by our Lady, by the Maſſe,</hi> or <hi>by my George,</hi> which binde (yet make guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the ſwearer) in relation the Creatures have to the Creator, (5.) In regard whereof, neither <hi>Pope, Prince, or Potentate,</hi> hath any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to diſpenſe: for ſuch caſes are reſerved onely to God, whoſe intereſt Man muſt not preſume to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench upon, except he will
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115443:47"/>deal (as the Devill did with our Saviour) and take upon him to give all Kingdomes, who had intereſt onely in Hells Dungeon. (6.) When therefore a contract by Oath, is between Superior, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Prince, and Subject, or Equall, bargaining one with another; or promiſes are made on conditions, or by parties not in their owne diſpoſition; if the Superior dye, or ceaſe to be ſuch, or the parties concerned give up their intereſt, or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at firſt, poſſible, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the contract prove unpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, or of ſcandalous, or damnable conſequence, or the act of the party, under government, be diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his lawfull Guardian, the Oath may be truly ſaid to be void, and the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence disburdened of it, not
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115443:47"/>by <hi>mans diſpenſation,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxation, but by <hi>Gods diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> who hath appointed oathes as a part of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to end controverſies, not to intangle conſciences. (7.) Laſtly, an oath taken to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that is wicked, as that <hi>of the Jewiſh Zealots to kill</hi> S. <hi>Paul,</hi> or to abandone that which is good, As a man to ſweare he will never ſerve his Prince, come neer his wife, help his children, or friends, (which by all tyes of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and morality he is bound to doe) the band lyes ſtill upon his conſcience to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate his damnable raſhnes in taking ſuch an oath, with all <hi>conſcionable repentance,</hi> not to execute that which he hath ſworne: leſt by thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to decline <hi>perjury,</hi> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre a more <hi>damnable abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. Herod</hi> had better
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:115443:48"/>have broken his oath, then ſo barbarousſly have murdered <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> bleſſed the advice of <hi>Abigail,</hi> that was a meanes to put him off from that he had vowed to God, to performe. And <hi>Saul</hi> was content with the peoples mutiny in a manner, that plucked <hi>Prince Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than away,</hi> from undergoing the doome of fury <hi>under Zeales vizard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">C. V.</note>
                  <hi>Touching the</hi> fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can any ſay,</hi> Lord have mercy upon us, and incline our hearts to keepe this law, <hi>when it is confeſſed, that the day is changed, and the praeciſe obſervation of the letter would neceſſarily caſt us back upon the obſervation of the</hi> Jewiſh Sabbath, <hi>turning our</hi> Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes <hi>into</hi> Saturdayes, <hi>there being neither praecept, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115443:48"/>to direct us otherwiſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note>In the <hi>Sabbath</hi> two things are conſiderable, (1.) the <hi>day,</hi> and (2.) <hi>rest.</hi> The <hi>day,</hi> by the analogy manifeſted in the commandement, is to be one in ſeven, according to the patterne given by God. The <hi>reſt</hi> is oppoſed to ſuch worldly labour, as might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way hinder it; but not as though it were ſet aſide to all employment, or might be ſpent in ſleep, or idleneſſe, or (that which we call paſtimes: but employed, it muſt be, in workes of <hi>ſanctity,</hi> not to be diverted, or retarded by our ſelves, or any that belong unto us, in buſineſſes of our ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nary vocation. This <hi>rest</hi> muſt ever be taken for <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> for all mens conſciences will give them, that <hi>publick worſhip</hi> is as due to God, and ſhould be performed with
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115443:49"/>more ſolemnity then <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate.</hi> This cannot be done without <hi>time</hi> &amp; <hi>place</hi> ſo ſet, that the aſſembling may be certain. But the <hi>duty</hi> ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, the <hi>day</hi> was altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: eſpecially by him, who profeſſeth himſelf, <hi>Lord of the Sabbath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 12.8.</note> Matth. 12.8. and therefore might well ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the, <hi>Lords day</hi> inſtead thereof. This day the acts of the Apoſtles confirmed, by the keeping of it; and their ſucceſſors have continued it, as of divine ordinance, in all Churches; which ſo muſt ſtand,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.10.</note> till it bring us to the perpetuall Sabbath of the Church triumphant. When we ſay therefore at the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of this commandement, <hi>Lord incline our hearts to keep this law,</hi> our meaning is, the morality of this law, which is, an enlivening, as it were
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115443:49"/>to all the reſt, not as the day was ſet the Jewes; to be the ſeventh from the creation, but as it was altered by our Saviour, and his Apoſtles practiſe, in regard of his <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reſurrection,</hi> from that reſting in the grave, to which the <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath</hi> had refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. So that <hi>typicall Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> might well give place to that <hi>Sunday.</hi> For which change, thoſe that call for a precept, muſt learne, that <hi>patternes</hi> may be as warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in matters of order, as <hi>precepts</hi> in the Articles of the Creed, <hi>the acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles being as canonicall as the foure Evangeliſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the ſame commandement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. VI.</note> 
                  <hi>the text expreſſely giving in charge,</hi> ſix dayes ſhalt thou labour, and doe all that thou haſt to doe, <hi>what warrant may a pious conſcience finde,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:115443:50"/>for keeping any holidayes any time of the weeke, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with greater ſolemnity, then the Lords day it ſelf is ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note>Thoſe words are not to be taken as a command, but to be received in this ſenſe. I have allotted thee a vocation in whatſoever condition thou art, and allow none to be idle, but to walke as I have called him. To performe which duty, for thine owne occaſions ſix dayes are allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee: But the ſeventh I refer wholly for mine owne ſervice, and command all thy ſecular buſineſſe to be laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, the more punctually to attend on it. Where we find that of the time left to our diſpoſe; if we, upon good grounds for extraordinary bleſſings appoint a day, or more, for prayer, praiſe, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115443:50"/>thanksgiving, we have the patterne of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the practiſe of our Saviour, who honoured with his preſence, and preaching the feaſt of the <hi>dedication,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jo: 10.22 Macchab. 4.59.</note> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined by the <hi>Machabees.</hi> And for that we are taught, and know, <hi>that right deare in the ſight of the Lord are the death of his Saints,</hi> as their lives have been honourable. And the righteous God hath ſo done, and doth his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veilous works, that they ought to be had in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: What heavenly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages may be taken, for ſetting forth Gods praiſes in his Saints? And ſtir up men to imitate ſuch excellent guides, and to glorifie the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of all in the beſt expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we may. Thoſe conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, little conſider, that make no conſcience on their owne
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115443:51"/>heads to call men from their vocations, to their affected aſſemblies, upon any day of the weeke, and yet murmure at the Church, for celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the memory (I ſay) not of Saints, and Martyrs, but of our <hi>Saviours Nativity,</hi> and aſcenſion, as though it carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it ſuperſtition.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">C. VII.</note>
                  <hi>The</hi> fifth Commandement <hi>is acknowledged by all, to give in charge the duties of all infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors to their lawfull ſuperiors, the due performance of which, is backed with a promiſe of long life, and enjoyments of ſuch poſſeſsions, as God hath beſtowed on all in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall callings. But if ſuch ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors renouncing God, and all goodneſſe, endeavour the oppreſsion, and ruine of thoſe they ſhould protect, are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors in ſuch caſes bound in conſcience to reſiſt, for their
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115443:51"/>owne preſervation, and force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to oppoſe them, if the caſe require it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Pauls deciſion</hi> is herein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe for the <hi>negative,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note> Rom. 13.1, 2. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the higher powers,</hi> as being Gods ordinance, and cannot be reſiſted without the penalty of <hi>Damnation.</hi> But what and they prove ſo intollerable, that to yeeld to them, ſhould be the undoing of our ſelves and ours? Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Saint <hi>Peter</hi> will afford no diſpenſation for this giving honour, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion: which muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, not only for our owne quietneſſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, but for the Lords ſake, and not <hi>to Kings only that are ſupreame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and have no ſuperiour judg to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to but only God;</hi> but alſo to ſuch governours as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115443:52"/>they ſhall put in commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether gentle, or fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, muſt be reſpected with due reverence in their places. <hi>For this is thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy</hi> (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle) <hi>if a man, for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God, endure grief, ſuffering wrongfully.</hi> He addes the example of our ſaviour for confirmation. <hi>For hereunto were ye called</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>becauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example that we ſhould follow his steps.</hi> Which how ſincere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly they doe, that corrupt old texts with new gloſſes, judg where they ſhould be judged: and put that to the queſtion, and carry it how they pleaſe, which never heretofore was doubted of, their owne conſcience will tell them one day, when they ſhall be called to repetitions.</p>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:115443:52"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Caſes concerning the five Commandements of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table.</head>
                  <p>THe precepts of the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table</hi> have rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and equals, as thoſe of the firſt had to our Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors. Which neighbour muſt not be wronged of us, (1.) in his life, by murder, (2.) in his wife, by adultery, (3.) in his goods, by ſtealing from him, (4.) in his good name, by bearing falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt him, (5.) no not ſo much as in deſire. But our utmoſt endeavor muſt be, for preſerving all theſe bleſſings in life, wife, goods, and good name unto him: being contented on our part, with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115443:53"/>what God hath bleſſed us with, in all thoſe particulars; not wiſhing to better our eſtates, by the diminiſhing of anothers, nor grudging that our neighbour enjoyes more plenty, then our ſelves, but holding, that which God hath ſent us, to be the fitteſt portion for us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning then this</hi> ſixt Commandement <hi>of the ten,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. I.</note> 
                     <hi>and first (as we reckon) of the ſecond Table,</hi> Thou ſhalt doe no murther, <hi>that is, thou ſhalt in no ſort wrong thy Brother touching his life, but doe the beſt to preſerve it, a ſcruple may be raiſed, Whether a man upon any pretenſe to avoid any inconvenience, or to attain any bettering of his eſtate, may be his owne executioner, and make himſelfe away?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He may not,<note place="margin">D.</note> and that by vertue of this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115443:53"/>For if our love to our Neighbour, muſt be patter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the love we beare our ſelves, according to that, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> Then if thy Neighbour may not be ſlain by thee, neither any violence or injury offered unto him tending that way, much leſſe canſt thou in conſcience kill thy ſelfe, or uſe any meanes on purpoſe to ſhorten thy dayes, be the pretext never ſo ſpecious, (2.) Inſtances out of Scripture, (1.) of <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> (2.) <hi>Saul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Mach. 6.46.2.14.37.</note> (3) his <hi>armour-bearer,</hi> (4.) <hi>Eleazar Savaran's</hi> Deſperate adventure upon an Elephant, (5.) <hi>Razis,</hi> and (6.) <hi>Judas Iſcariot,</hi> yeild not the Leaſt excuſe for ſo unnaturall a fact. For though ſomewhat may be ſaid for <hi>Sampſon,</hi> that he intended not his owne death, but revenge on his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115443:54"/>as <hi>Eleazar</hi> did the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Countrey, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; yet <hi>Razis</hi> violence can hardly be excuſed, <hi>Saul's</hi> and his <hi>armour-bearers</hi> muſt needs be condemned. <hi>Achitophels</hi> is ſet up, for a patterne for all <hi>perfidious politicians</hi> to take example by, and <hi>Judas</hi> left as a monument to the terror of all <hi>traytors, that buy and ſell their Maſters.</hi> (3.) Thoſe that through drinking, drabbing, or needleſſe quarrelling, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten their owne ends; as alſo through peeviſh vowes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected ſorrow, or wayward melancholy dammes, neglect their owne preſervation, by all decent meanes offered, may doe well to conſult with their owne conſciences, whether they come not within the compaſſe of this command, <hi>thou ſhalt not commit murder,</hi> neither on thy ſelf nor others.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:115443:54"/>But of others more hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>Next the preſervation of Gods image, in being tender of mans life, the upholding and keeping his temple from pollution is eſpecially to be reſpected, which is done in this ſeventh commandement, <hi>thou ſhalt not commit adultery,</hi> wherein not only all kind of uncleanneſſe, and incitements thereunto tending, and allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring are utterly forbidden: But modeſty, ſhame faceneſſe, and continency in thought, word, and deed, are eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In which this ſcruple may firſt ariſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whether marriages within</hi> degrees of conſanguinity, or affinity prohibited, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. or of patties <hi>ſeparated after lawfull wedlock,</hi> while both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine alive, <hi>or</hi> polygamie <hi>that multiplyeth the couple, that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115443:55"/>ſhould make but one fleſh, in conſcience may be condemned, as adulterous?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſafeſt tenent is that they may and ought.<note place="margin">D.</note> For theſe prohibited degrees, in <hi>Leviticus</hi> are urged by God, as the dictates of nature, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended as well to all gentiles, as Jewes, by the text it ſelf. <hi>For all thoſe abhominations have the men of the land done which were before you,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lev. 1 8 27 &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>and the land is defiled.</hi> For which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences they were ſpewed out, and that ſoule ſhall be cut off from among his people, that is found in the like tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. (2.) Then for the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluble bond of wedlock, but only by death, our Saviour and the Apoſtle are ſo pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, that it ſhould terrify any one free to marry a party divorced, and not by death ſeperated. <hi>Fornication indeed
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:115443:55"/>may make a ſeparation, but not juſtifie the marrying of the party innocent.</hi> Why may not upon repentance, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of the party of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, a Chriſtian recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation be made? after which, if fornication prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent had diſſolved the band, a new marriage of the party ſo diſſolved muſt be made, before they may lawfully come againe together, as man and wife. Beſide this openeth a gap to wicked people, that are weary of their firſt engagement, by wickedneſſe to make a way for freeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves of it, to ſatisfie their leudneſs, under a pretence of law. And (3.) for <hi>Polygamy,</hi> or taking more wives then one at a time, the examples of the fathers of the old Teſtament cannot ſatisfy the conſcience of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:115443:56"/>thoſe, who live under the New, being taught by our Saviour, <hi>that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it was not ſo:</hi> but two only were appointed to be one fleſh. And therefore what was not taxed in good men, but borne with in Gods not revealed deſignes, muſt not make a rule for poſterity, who are tyed to follow Gods precepts, not all the beſt mens actions in caſes of conſcience: accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Apoſtles limited exhortation,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Be ye followers of me, as I am a follower of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whether painting,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. III.</note> 
                     <hi>or patch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the face, criſping and curling of the hayre, expoſing the nakedneſſe of the neck or paps (which as attractives or incentives unto luſtfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires) eſpecially by ſuch wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that have husbands; and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:115443:56"/>that in publick aſſemblies, in conſcience may be uſed, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In matters of indifferency,<note place="margin">D.</note> cuſtome, &amp; ſhunning ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity may pick out ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe. But thoſe, who ſhall conſider the cenſure paſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the daughters of Sion in that behalf, by the Prophet, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3. and the wholſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction left by the Apoſtle to wives, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. (which others alſo may doe well to follow) <hi>whoſe adorning, let it not be that outward ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of playting the haire, and in wearing of gold, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on of apparell, but let it be the hidden man of the heart (in that which is not corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) even the ornament of a meeke, and quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price,</hi> will be very cautious how they adventure in this
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:115443:57"/>particular; ſurely the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> would have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to have admitted ſuch garments, as now Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition adornes her Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues with to ſet her forth, for ſpiritual fornication. And S. <hi>James</hi> would have cryed out, at the ſights in theſe times,<note place="margin">Matt. 11.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Ye adulterers, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultereſſes, know ye not that the friendſhip of the world is enmity with God? Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver therefore will be a friend of the world, is an enemy of God.</hi> Jam. 4.4. Our Saviour taxeth not the ſoft rayment of thoſe that dwelt in <hi>Kings houſes,</hi> whereby differences of places, and degrees are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly diſtinguiſhed; but thereupon to paint with <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabell,</hi> and riot with <hi>Dives,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 3.3.</note> and leave <hi>poore Lazarus</hi> to the dogs proviſion, this is to put on a <hi>Whores fore-head,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:115443:57"/>all modeſty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whether dancing of men and women together,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. IV.</note> 
                     <hi>frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtage-playes, enterteyning laſcivious ſongs, delighting in idle Romancies of love-bookes, or the like, come not as much within the compaſſe of this commandement, as the looking upon a woman, and the luſting after her? which our Saviour pronounceth to be adultery in the heart.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 5.28.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a ſaying among Philoſophers,<note place="margin">D.</note> things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly prove as they are taken. <hi>Dancing of men with women,</hi> why may it not be as harmleſſe as the ſitting of them together at the Table, or in other aſſemblies? And what prohibition have we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Stage-playes,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cautelouſly penned, and decently acted, they ſhould
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:115443:58"/>not paſſe for commendable recreation, for thoſe that are fit ſpectators of them? So well contrived, and well languaged <hi>Romances</hi> (as ſome terme them) may be allowed to be read, by thoſe that know to make uſe of <hi>parabolicall, and emblematicall Propoſalls.</hi> They ſtate not the queſtion, that <hi>decry wine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Drunkards abuſe it.</hi> Old mens <hi>ſtoicall ſewerneſſe</hi> muſt not blame <hi>Saint Paul</hi>'s con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed weakneſſe, that <hi>when he was a child, he ſpake as a child, he underſtood as a child, and thought as a child,</hi> 1 Cor: 13.11. But rather endeavour, by all religious inducements, to draw thoſe that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come men, to put away childiſhnes. Let young <hi>Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> goe with the King (ſaith old <hi>Barzillai</hi>) and turne Courtier to ſerve his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:115443:58"/>
                     <hi>But I that am a man of foure ſcore,</hi> and now paſt feaſting, or hearing any more <hi>the voice of Singing men, and ſinging women, let me goe home, and be buried with my anceſtors,</hi> 2 Sam: 19.35. And that wiſe <hi>King-preacher</hi> (as well gifted as any in theſe dayes) hath told all poſterity, that as there is <hi>a time to weep, ſo there is a time to laugh,</hi> and as there is <hi>a time to mourne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.4.</note> ſo there is <hi>a time to dance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The eight Commandment, <hi>thou ſhalt not ſteale,</hi> bringeth us from the conflicts of the fleſh, confined in the former precept, to the dealings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the world, to try how conſcience will be there eſteemed of. Wherein the caſes of Sacriledge, abuſing things conſecrated to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane uſes, (2.) cheating, or cozening in all ſorts of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:115443:59"/>(3.) diverting, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving the true owners of their right, being of ſpeciall note, this one queſtion will ſerve in ſtead of many.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With what conſcience</hi> Lay-Impropriators <hi>withhold Tithes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. V.</note> 
                     <hi>or any other rights from the Church? or</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, <hi>and other tradeſ-men over-reach thoſe they contract with by any kind of deceit? Or</hi> careleſſe debters <hi>that take no courſe to pay their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or provide things honeſt, or befitting themſelves and families, and yet thinke to be freed from the breach, and penalty, not from the</hi> burning in the hand <hi>only, but from</hi> the burning in the heart <hi>for</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious thieves?</p>
                  <p>Thoſe that are found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in theſe,<note place="margin">D.</note> and the like crimes, have no other ſalve for a feſtering conſcience,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:115443:59"/>then that <hi>Joſhuah</hi> adviſed <hi>Achan</hi> unto, to take off the venome of his ſacriledge. <hi>My ſon give glory to God, make Confeſsion what thou haſt done, that Satisfaction may be made, before thou, and thine be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly undone.</hi> Ioſ: 7.19. The accuſer will be found to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce the evidence, till Satisfaction be made. <hi>Will a man rob his God? but ye ſay, wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes, and offerings.</hi> (But what of that? We have law to back us, yet marke what followes) <hi>Ye are curſed with a curſe; for ye have robbed me, even this whole Nation, Mal.</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked, he is a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, and who will juſtifie where he condemneth?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov 11.1. Lev. 19.36 Deut. 25.15 Pro. 16.11.20.10.23. Rom. 13.8.</note> Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvention and <hi>fraud,</hi> or any kind of cheating by <hi>weights,</hi> or balances, or <hi>ſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhetorick,</hi>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:115443:60"/>he taketh for no other then <hi>ſmooth theft;</hi> And will have his ſervants to <hi>owe nothing to any man, but that they love one another.</hi> He that is quitted by <hi>humane preceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> may be caſt and hanged at the <hi>Bar of Conſcience;</hi> which will never ceaſe to be clamorous here, nor gnaw as a worme hereafter; if ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction be not made, not by poore put-offs, but reall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment, and reſtitution.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the</hi> ninth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,<note place="margin">C. VI.</note> 
                     <hi>which forbids us to wrong our neighbours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by any means, under the expreſion of</hi> bearing falſe witneſſe:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.15</note> 
                     <hi>and enjoyneth us to ſpeak the truth by all means in love, for the ſetting forth of Gods glory, and the good of our ſelves and others. The Caſe may be, whether the meaning of it be ſo rigidly to be taken,</hi>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:115443:60"/>(1.) <hi>That the telling an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth by</hi> Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Iſaac <hi>to ſave their Wives chaſtity:</hi> (2.) <hi>By</hi> Jacob <hi>to beguile his brother of his</hi> bleſſing: (3.) <hi>Of the</hi> Aegyptian <hi>Midwives to ſave poor</hi> infants from drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: (4) <hi>Of</hi> Rahab, <hi>and the good woman of</hi> Bahurim <hi>for protecting of the</hi> faithfull State-meſſengers: (5.) <hi>Of</hi> Chuſai, <hi>for defeating the</hi> treacherous deſignes of the ſon againſt the father: (6.) <hi>Of</hi> Jehu, <hi>for</hi> grubbing up the Baalites <hi>root and branch:</hi> (7.) <hi>Of</hi> Ananias, <hi>and</hi> Sapphira, <hi>to keep ſomething about them, to truſt to, howſoever things ſhould fall out, may not with a ſafe conſcience be followed? The like may be held of</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences <hi>making ſhew of one thing, and meaning another, as that of</hi> Jaell to Siſerah, <hi>and the</hi> ſeeming of our Saviour,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:115443:61"/>
                     <hi>who made as if he would have gone further, to the diſciples, travailing to Emaus, yet by the event may be gathered, meant no ſuch matter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">D.</note> the chief thing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden under the name of <hi>falſe witneſſe,</hi> are conſented by all to be either, (1.) <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious,</hi> (2.) <hi>officious,</hi> (3.) <hi>flaſhes of wit to make ſport.</hi> The <hi>pernicious</hi> lye, that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the apparent wrong of any one, is condemned by all: but an <hi>officious</hi> lye, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on an occaſion to doe a deed of mercy, or preventing of an imminent miſchief, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> that merriment of the third ſort of <hi>jesting</hi> lyes for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations to ſhew wit, or make ſport, are exempted by diverſe from the mark of ſin, and ſo taken off from the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction of this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But the better groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:115443:61"/>opinion is, that no lye of what kind ſoever can be juſtified. For the text is plaine, <hi>ye ſhall not ſteale, nor deale falſely,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lev. 19.19.11</note> 
                     <hi>nor lye one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>another.</hi> Put away lying, ſpeake every man truth with his neighbour, For we are members one of another: and members of the ſame body ſhould naturally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur, for the preſervation of the whole, which conſiſteth in mutuall agreement. And when lyars come to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, there will be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance out of doubt had, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportion of wrong done, or intended, without any diſtinction, or exemption. <hi>Lyars</hi> are chain'd amongſt the <hi>fearfull</hi> to ſtand up for Gods truth,<note place="margin">Revel: 21. 8</note> amongſt <hi>infidels,</hi> and <hi>abhominable,</hi> amongſt <hi>murderers,</hi> and <hi>whore-mongers, ſorcerers,</hi> and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:115443:62"/>
                     <hi>idolaters,</hi> which ſhall have their portion in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death. Now, for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the inſtances given, which ſeem to make ſome lies paſſeable. Howſoever, Apologies in particular may be made to excuſe them from being lies, this generall rule may ſerve, <hi>That where the Scripture ſets downe Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorically, that which hath been done, without manifeſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it: the deed with all the circumſtances is not a dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, or warrant for our man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which are to be guided by Gods precepts, not by Mans practice:</hi> for the beſt mens actions may have ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection in the carriage, which Gods infinite wiſdom turns to his owne glory, not
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:115443:62"/>propoſeth to us for imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where precept is to the contrary. Our Saviour told not the travellers to <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maus,</hi> that he would goe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but they conceived by his poſture, that he would, which he took on him not to deceive them, but to quicken their deſires, to retaine that which he had purpoſed to doe for their good. Let this Caſe of Conſcience lie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt all ſort of collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whether in ſport, or earneſt; for Gods truth is not to be played with, but as the <hi>third Commandement</hi> beats down <hi>ſwearing</hi> to Gods dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, ſo this <hi>ninth</hi> allows no <hi>lying,</hi> whereby truth and plain dealing with any one may ſuffer injury.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>laſt commandement</hi> puts the ax to the root of the tree, and excepteth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:115443:63"/>externall acts, with internall purpoſes, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: but the very motions of corrupted nature, that bubble up againſt Gods law. So that originall ſin is here as it were knocked on the head, leſt the cockatrice, not cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the egge, might prove a maſterleſſe ſerpent. The vertues here preſcribed are a hearty ſubmiſſion to Gods command, without the leaſt regret within, and a content with outward meanes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grudging at others more happy condition. Whence the caſe may ariſe,<note place="margin">C. VII</note> 
                     <hi>whether we may (which is done too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) wiſh, with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that any thing ſhould be withdrawn from our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to his prejudice, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon us, who reſt not content with what God hath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:115443:63"/>
                  <p>Such <hi>wiſhes, concupiſcence,</hi> or <hi>deſires,</hi> are the <hi>ſeeds of all miſchiefs,</hi> and have their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration in <hi>touching, tickling,</hi> and <hi>tarrying thoughts,</hi> from which ariſe deſire, <hi>aſſent, and action.</hi> For the two laſt of which, that is, <hi>aſſent and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the precedent comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements take ſufficient or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: but here the <hi>involuntary motion,</hi> and pronenes to ſin without conſent is taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of and cenſured; that man may be carefull of his moſt retired plots, ſeeing the ſearcher, and tryer of the heart and reines calls all to a reckoning.<note place="margin">Philip: 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>I have learned</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>in what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſoever I am, therewithall to he content.</hi> That which our <hi>Saviour</hi> put off the tempting, entrapping Phariſees, and <hi>Herodians</hi> with,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21</note> 
                     <hi>give unto Caeſar the things that are Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:115443:64"/>and to God the things that are Gods,</hi> may ſerve by way of arbitration to direct our conſcience in this behalf. Let our affections thus reſolve. I am fully content with that houſe, wife, ſervants, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or any other thing that God hath bleſſed me with. I heartily thank him for it, and beſeech him that I may ſo improve it, that my reckoning at the laſt account may receive a, Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etus eſt, or approbation. And let my neighbour enjoy his on Gods name, whether it be more, or leſſe then I have, or he uſeth aright. To behave our ſelves otherwiſe were to queſtion Gods wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and grudge at his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution, who giveth and taketh away not according to our appetites and fancy. Not our wiſhes, therefore,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:115443:64"/>wild and witleſſe, but his will muſt: be, that a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhould alwayes wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Which if it were done, it would prevent the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold law-ſuites, and quarrels, that breed ſo much vexation, and diſaſters among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an neighbourhood; and ſet a good tune to that paſſage of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Turn again then unto thy reſt O my ſoul, for the Lord hath rewarded thee! And why? thou haſt delivered my ſoule from death, mine eyes from teares, and my feet from falling, that I may walke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in the land of the living, Pſal.</hi> 116.7.8.9.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:115443:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Caſes upon conſideration of the Lords Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRom the first word</hi> our (<hi>as it lyeth in our language) and holdes forth a generall,<note place="margin">C. I.</note> without exception, ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may haply ſcruple, whether it be lawfull to pray for all ſorts of people, without diſtinction, amongſt whom ſome are departed this life, and can receive no benefit by our prayers, others may have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against the Holy ghoſt, and God's decree is paſt upon them, for whom we are not to pray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An <hi>evill</hi> man,<note place="margin">D.</note> in an <hi>evill</hi> way, petitioning for an <hi>evill</hi> thing, may ſpeed no better then <hi>Bathſheba</hi> did for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniah,</hi> in her ſuit to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:115443:65"/>to give him <hi>Abiſhag</hi> to wife: charity in our praiers is to be underſtood to extend no further, then Gods word doth limit it. To pray for the dead, who have their immutable doom, we have no warrant. It is ſufficient ground therefore for our conſcience in this behalf, that <hi>God would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledg of his truth,</hi> to make it a petition in our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, <hi>that it may pleaſe him to have mercy upon all men,</hi> we beſeech thee to hear us good Lord. Wherein we expreſſe our charitable deſires, leaving it to God to diſtinguiſh for whom our prayers ſhall be effectuall. A further directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be that of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to his Diſciples;<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.11, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>if ye come into a houſe, ſalute it, and if the houſe be worthy, let
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:115443:66"/>your peace come upon it, but if the houſe be not worthy, let your peace returne to you.</hi> So our devotion in prayer for all ſhall be acceptable to our father, who maketh his <hi>ſun to riſe on the evill, as on the good; and his raine to fall on the unjust as on the juſt:</hi> though the ſaving benifit thereof ſhall redound only to thoſe, whom God hath appointed it ſhall take with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond word in our Lords prayer</hi> is,<note place="margin">C. II.</note> Father, <hi>which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to what perſon in the bleſſed Trinity, we ſhould direct our prayers. This prayer then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only a prayer to be uſed of all, but alſo a patterne to all, what warrant then hath a ſcrupulous conſcience to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect its prayers (not to Saints, or Angells, or any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for that good Chriſtians are eaſily ſatisfied in, but either)
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:115443:66"/>to the Son, or holy Ghoſt? in as much as we are preciſely to keep to the rule which our Saviour hath left us, and not to frame other devotions, how religion ſoever they may ſeeme to be, according to the model of our owne fancies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>ground</hi> being laid in our <hi>Creed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note> that the three Perſons, howſoever diſtinguiſhed, are but one, God: it will neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow thereupon, that whoſoever prayeth to one, prayeth to all: and all the perſons howſoever diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in themſelves, yet in relation to the creatures may be called Father. And beſide, for the directing of our prayers to the <hi>Son,</hi> we have that of Saint <hi>Stephen, Lord Jeſu receive my ſpirit,</hi> Act. 7.59. And for that of the <hi>holy Ghoſt, who gave a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement ſeparate me Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:115443:67"/>and Saul to the worke which I have called them,</hi> which muſt needs be taken for the command of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that was God, It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>after they had faſted and prayed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3.</note> to whom can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that they have prayed, but to him who gave the command?<note place="margin">Matth. 28.</note> This is confirmed by our baptizing equally in the name of the holy Ghoſt, as of the Father, and Son: and by S. <hi>Pauls</hi> bleſſing, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in equally the Holy Ghoſt, with the Father, and the Son. Where he maketh this as his ordinary bleſſing, <hi>The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.14</note> 
                  <hi>and the love of God, and the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt be with you all.</hi> Where the putting of Jeſus Chriſt before the Father plainly ſheweth, that (as we have it in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Creed) in this
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:115443:67"/>myſterious, and ſacred Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, none is afore, or after another, none is greater or leſſe then other. That which is done therefore to one, is done to all. For which that attribute, in the prayer of the Apoſtles, may be taken for a further ground. The Text is, <hi>they prayed, and ſaid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>thou Lord which knoweſt the hearts of all men.</hi> To him that knoweth therefore our hearts, and to no other, we may ſafely direct our prayer; and who will deny that the Holy Ghoſt knoweth our hearts? which is ſaid to guide, and lead into all truth. That petition therefore in our Liturgy, with the like, <hi>O God the Holy Ghoſt, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Father, and the Son, have mercy upon us mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinners:</hi> and the Doxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy ſo often repeated, <hi>glory
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:115443:68"/>be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost,</hi> cannot be excepted againſt, but only by ſuch wretches, which deny the Sacred Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Notwithſtanding as ſome prayers are private, of, or by our ſelves: others publick, with the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: As private prayers are, uſually, not neceſſarily, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to either of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: So publick are moſt orderly in the firſt place ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to the Father, through our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, that he will vouchſafe us his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to furniſh us with all bleſſings, to accompliſh all our warrantable petitions. And according to this are all, or moſt of our <hi>Liturgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> petitions framed, which in an uniformity ſhew the order of the Perſons in the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:115443:68"/>Trinity, and prevent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, which might ariſe amongſt the weaker by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of variety.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From the firſt petition,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. III.</note> hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy name, <hi>may ariſe this doubt. That in as much as our Saviour approved of ſuch as caſt out devills in his name, yet followed him not, and would not have them forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: and the Jewes attribute, even at this day, a virtue to the name</hi> Jehovah, <hi>that mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles may be done by it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof, in reverence they dare not to utter it: Why may not we thinke that the</hi> name of God <hi>uſed by Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and exorcists gathered by</hi> Cabala <hi>from the Scripture, may worke wonders in caſting out divills, curing diſeaſes, and foretelling events, and thereupon with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience have recourſe to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:115443:69"/>for aid in that behalfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>name of God,</hi> in the ſcripture, eſpecially impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>propriety, authority, and ability.</hi> So that being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, <hi>in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> we are made Gods peculiar, to ſubmit to his authority, under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of his omnipotent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. In this petition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, as fooliſh, as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, by <hi>the name of God</hi> to underſtand, from the coupling of the letters, the ſound reſulting from it; or to imagine an hidden virtue to be in the characters, or ſound of words, to terrifie ſpirits or worke other won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. The <hi>hallowing of Gods name</hi> is the ſetting forth of Gods glory, in all his attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, to which all our peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions muſt be referred, that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:115443:69"/>his kingdome in his Church may be promoted here, to be perfected hereafter in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and his will be done in order, according as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in his word. Which warrantable directions we have from that guide that will not deceive. <hi>Saul</hi> will get cold comfort by conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the <hi>witch of Endor:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam 28. 2 Kings. 1</note> or <hi>Ahaziah</hi> by ſending to <hi>Beelzebub of Ekron.</hi> Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour reproveth, rather the aemulous jealouſie of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, then approveth of the parties that made uſe of his name, whom they would not follow. Concerning which we have his cenſure, <hi>many will ſay unto me in that day, Lord, Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 7.22</note> 
                  <hi>have we not prophecied in thy name? And in thy name caſt out devills? And in thy name done many wonderfull workes? I then
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:115443:70"/>will profeſſe unto them I never knew you, depart from me all ye that worke iniquity.</hi> The ſeeking therefore to ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by Satan, and delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding others, is a departure from God, wherein he, that turnes himſelfe into an <hi>Angel of light,</hi> will be found at length to be the Prince of darkneſſe, worſe then <hi>a light angel,</hi> and will help the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſtate no further, then to gaine upon the ſoule to its eternall ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whereas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. IV.</note> 
                  <hi>in</hi> the fourth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, <hi>we beg for our ſelves, all things neceſſary for our corporall ſustenance, under the name of</hi> daily bread, <hi>that frugality may be thought to be juſtly implyed: which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes any extraordinary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations in feastings, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, building, more then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity requireth; with what
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:115443:70"/>conſcience can we goe beyond that we daily deſire? Since ſuch ſuperfluities, our Saviour telleth us,</hi> the nations of the world ſeeke after, <hi>and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles rule is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.20 1 Tim. 6.8.</note> having food and rayment, let us be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with content.</p>
               <p>Herein the circumſtances of time, place, our abilities,<note place="margin">D.</note> condition of eſtate, and life, with the end, why ſometime the ordinary courſe is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, varieth the caſe.<note place="margin">Gen. 18.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> for enterteyning the angells made better then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary proviſion: and at the <hi>weaning of Iſaac</hi> made a great feaſt. And what extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary diet there was at the time of ſhearing their ſheep,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 2 Sam. 13.</note> the ſtory of <hi>Nabal</hi> and <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſufficiently declare. To this purpoſe, that <hi>chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up of Nehemiah</hi> to the people that mourned at the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:115443:71"/>hearing of the law, which they had tranſgreſſed, is worth the noting. <hi>Goe your way, eate the fat, and drinke the ſweet, and ſend portions to them, for whom nothing is prepared: for this day is holy unto the Lord. Nehem.</hi> 8.10. And the good father in the Goſpel thought his beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion not good enough, for the welcoming home his <hi>pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent prodigal:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 15.25</note> but Muſick, and Dancing muſt be had for the complement of the feſtivity, and gladneſſe. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences therefore in this caſe muſt be conſidered, either in an ordinary courſe of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſo they are to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by a temperate fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, and diſcretion, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeverall eſtates of men or condition: or upon juſt cauſes of augmentation, or ſparing. For as there is
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:115443:71"/>variety of bread, apparell, and calling; ſo the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance muſt be meaſured ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. Our Saviour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited himſelfe to <hi>Zachaeus</hi> houſe,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.</note> who ſtrained himſelf out of doubt, to give his beſt entertainment, and it was wel taken: but <hi>Judas</hi> had a check for blaming <hi>Holy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry's</hi> profuſeneſſe.<note place="margin">Jo. 12.4.</note> How ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous was the <hi>Bleſſed mother,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 2.</note> that the marriage feaſt ſhould not be diſcredited, for want of wine? And how unexpectedly did our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſupply it? <hi>Feaſts</hi> then and <hi>triumphs</hi> may be often celebrated, in due time, and place, by thoſe whom it may concerne, for expreſſing our thankfulneſſe to God, and praiſing his bounty: as faſts, and humiliations are, on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions, to turne away his indignation from us, by
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:115443:72"/>our hearty repentance. <hi>The kingdome of God conſiſteth not in eating, and drinking.</hi> Let all be done to Gods glory, as he hath preſcribed. <hi>Daily bread,</hi> here, is to be taken, for the portion fit for every ones condition. Then as in the ordering of Mannah, he that had gathered much, had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing over, and he that had gathered little, had no lack.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If our</hi> treſpaſſes,<note place="margin">C. V.</note> 
                  <hi>or debts, are deſired to be forgiven us by God, no otherwiſe then we are content to forgive our debtors, or thoſe that have</hi> treſpaſſed againſt us: <hi>with what conſcience then can we ſue for our debts, or proſecute thoſe that any way have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, or Lawyers take fees for the promoting of ſuch?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Offences,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note> or <hi>debts</hi> may be ſuch, as either intrench upon
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:115443:72"/>Gods glory, Church, or Word, in which all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have an intereſt, and we are not to forgive, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; but tyed to proſecute the offenders, that ſo they may be brought to a juſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, according to our power, or condition. Other <hi>differences, and debts</hi> there may be, wherein our <hi>perſons</hi> are only concerned, without the leaſt prejudice to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and theſe only are here required to be remitted, that our ſuit may have no demur at the throne of grace. We find what a great ſum was remitted to the penitent debtor, upon his free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his faithfull endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſatisfie. But when he fell ſo foulely upon his indebted brother, O! what a heavy doome the mercifull
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:115443:73"/>Lord laid upon him. <hi>O! Thou wicked ſervant, I forgave thee all that debt, becauſe thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiredſt me: Shouldest not thou alſo have had compaſsion on thy fellow-ſervant, even as I had pity en thee?</hi> Now <hi>debts, that are due unto us,</hi> may be not only required for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of out owne neceſſity, but ſupport of our family, and retinue; who thereby have alſo in them an intereſt; and when a wrong done to my Perſon, ſtayeth not there, but doth reflect upon my calling, and reputation, which I am bound to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and often breaketh out further, to the diſhonour of God himſelfe, or of his Church, or word, the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the wicked, and ſcandall of the wel-affected, <hi>remiſsion</hi> in ſuch caſes may prove ſo unſeaſonable, that
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:115443:73"/>if juſtice be not executed to the utmoſt, it may cauſe the Sword thereof to turne back, and to prick him that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to put it up. Thus <hi>Saul</hi> was puniſhed for ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Agag,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.</note> and a lion killed that party that would not ſtrike,<note place="margin">1 King. 20.36.</note> when a Prophet from the Lord Commanded him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From the ſixth petition,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. VI.</note> Lead us not into Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>ſeeing it is apparent, that Temptations are from God, as they are from Satan: what Characters of difference may the conſcience find to diſcerne the one from the other, that it may make the true uſe of both to Gods glory, and his owne contentment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As, <hi>in the originall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D.</note> there is a maine difference between <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: ſo <hi>in our</hi> tongue a <hi>triall</hi> from a <hi>tentation</hi> hath an evident
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:115443:74"/>diſtinction. It was no tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Philip,</hi> when our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our put him the queſtion to try him; becauſe he himſelf knew what he would doe. <hi>Gods tempting</hi> therefore of <hi>Abraham</hi> was but to try, whether he preferred his Faith in him, before naturall affection to his onely Son. But <hi>Satans tempting</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> was to his ruine. The ſcope, and end of the Suggeſtion therefore is a ſufficient differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>tryall</hi> from God, and <hi>a plot</hi> from Satan. Saint <hi>James</hi> tells us, that when a man is tempted, he is not tempted of God. <hi>For God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>cannot be tempted of evill, neither tempteth he any man. But every man is tempted, when he is drawne away, and enticed,</hi> Jam. 1.13, 14. <hi>Such temptations</hi> are moſt commonly (1.) <hi>to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſse,</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:115443:74"/>(2.) <hi>to ſecuritie,</hi> (3.) <hi>to Vain-glory,</hi> (4.) <hi>to contempt of Gods word, and Miniſters,</hi> (5.) <hi>to revenge,</hi> (6) <hi>to Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> (7.) <hi>to deſpaire. Sampſon, Solomon, Achitophelly, Davids</hi> numbring of the people, he that built his barnes in the parable without thinking on the Author of his plenty, <hi>Achans</hi> ſacrilege without minding Gods inhibition, <hi>Judas</hi> executing himſelfe without conſideration of the mercy of his Maſter, are Sufficient inſtances from whom ſuch Temptations proceed. But <hi>Gods fiery tryall</hi> hath another iſſue of joy,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.12</note> and comfort, that we are made Partakers of Chriſt's ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, that when his Glory ſhall be revealed, we may be glad with exceeding joy. Our petition therefore to God is, that in conſideration of our
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:115443:75"/>owne weakneſſe, and the forces, and ſleights of our adverſaries, that he will not expoſe as to be tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that we are able: but, if it ſtand with his good pleaſure to try us, to make a way to eſcape, that we may be able to beare it. As he did to <hi>Job,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13</note> 
                  <hi>to his Diſciples, to the Martyrs,</hi> who have left their victorious trophees for us to imitate. <hi>But deliver us from evil.</hi> Some make this petition an explication of the former; and the ſenſe to be no other, but to be free from the dangers, that Temptations may caſt upon us. But the Ancient make it the ſeventh petition; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers take it in this ſenſe, that whereas formerly we beg Protection from ſeducing allurments of the world, and the fleſh, which can only
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:115443:75"/>flatter us into miſcheife: ſo here we ſue for garding pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, from the violent aſſaults of the devill, which <hi>goeth about</hi> night and day <hi>as a roaring lion, ſeeking whom he may devoure,</hi> and cannot be withſtood, but only by the <hi>lion of the tribe of Judah,</hi> who hath a chaine to bind him, and a kennell to coope him up, that a legion of them have not power to hurt a hog, without expreſſe leave. This interpretation the word favoureth, where it is in the original, <hi>deliver us from that evill, or that evill one,</hi> by an excellency termed the tempter.<note place="margin">C. VII.</note> Whence a ſcruple may ariſe. <hi>What is to be thought of thoſe that are commonly held poſſeſſed by the devill, or haunted with evill Spirits, and by what meanes we are bound in conſcience to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:115443:76"/>procure them releif, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eſpeciall care muſt be taken that there be no collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the buſineſſe.<note place="margin">D.</note> It is well knowne what <hi>Popiſh Priests</hi> have attempted in this kind, to re-eſtabliſh here amongſt us their <hi>Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> as alſo the <hi>diſciplinarians</hi> to overthrow our <hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Church government.</hi> But if upon due ſearch, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, ſuch poſſeſſion, or obſeſſion be found, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing muſt be thought upon to conjurers, white, or curing witches, or purring any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in crucifixes, holy water, conſecrated hoaſts, or charmes, bus by moſt humble, earneſt, perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring addreſſes to God, joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with faſting; which is the method preſcribed by Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.21. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:115443:76"/>this for our ground, <hi>Our Father, which art in heaven,</hi> deliver us from this grand evill. The <hi>woman of Canaan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 15.22.</note> herein is to be imitated. She applyeth her ſelfe directly to our Saviour, was not daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the uncomfortable interpoſition of the diſciples, <hi>ſend her away, for ſhe cryeth after us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 23.</note> gave not over ſuit upon our Saviours firſt put off, <hi>I am not ſent, but to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 24.</note> reſteth not upon a ſecond more harſh deniall,<note place="margin">v. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>it is not meet to take the childrens bread, and give to dogs:</hi> but perſevering obteins with a high commendation, <hi>woman great is thy faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>be it unto thee even as thou wilt,<note place="margin">v. 28.</note> and her daughter was made whole from that very houre.</hi> But here we are to looke, that fits of deep melancholy, of
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:115443:77"/>the mother, <hi>Epilepſies,</hi> &amp;c. be not miſtaken, for poſſeſſions of the devill. Phyſicians like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe here ſhould be conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, whoſe endeavours, accompanied with the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Divines, and good people, will give eaſe at leaſt and comfort, if not doe the cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Caſes upon the Sacraments.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAcraments</hi> are Signes of Gods favours, and ſeales of his covenants made with us for our ſalvation. Theſe, in the new Teſtament of our Saviours immediate inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be ſuch, are but two: the firſt of <hi>admiſsion,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception into the Church,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:115443:77"/>which is <hi>Baptiſme:</hi> the other of <hi>continuation,</hi> and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſame, and that is the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> both ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving plaine <hi>inſtitution</hi> from Chriſt, diſtinct <hi>Signes Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying,</hi> and <hi>Graces,</hi> and <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits</hi> Signified, and conferred by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And here (as preſumptuous Fanaticks have now bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed poore Christians) it may well be made a caſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the firſt place,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. I.</note> 
                  <hi>whether the</hi> Sacrament <hi>may be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred without a Miniſter law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called, and there be a nullity in the action that in this caſe is done by any other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this twofold propoſall we muſt give diſtinct an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.<note place="margin">D.</note> We know in the old Teſtament how hard it went with the 250 <hi>Intruders upon the Prieſthood,</hi> deſigned to the <hi>Levites, who periſhed in
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:115443:78"/>the contradiction of Corah.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 16.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul</hi> loſt his Kingdom with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a calling,<note place="margin">1 Sam 13.13.</note> and King <hi>Uzzah</hi> (otherwiſe a worthy Prince) carried the leproſy with him to his grave,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 26.16</note> for daring to burne incenſe upon the Altar, to the which he had no lawful call. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we have that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in the Hebrews,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.4.</note> 
                  <hi>No man taketh this Honour upon him, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron.</hi> Our Saviours command was onely to his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> that as they were to Preach the Goſpell, ſo were they to <hi>Baptize,</hi> in the name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt. And to his <hi>Diſciples</hi> only it was left to <hi>celebrate his Supper,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him, which all Churches have followed in their Succeſſors. To the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſcruple, if women, or
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:115443:78"/>other Lay-people, in defect of a Miniſter, ſhould take upon them to Baptize, yet doe it in a right way, before Men, the Baptiſme may be taken for good, though they ſinned that did it, becauſe the <hi>efficacy of the Sacrament</hi> dependeth upon Chriſt, that ordained it, not the <hi>Miniſter</hi> that gives it, provided that afterward it come under the examination, and approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Church.</hi> Few of the Laies have adventured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us to adminiſter the Lords Supper. But in ſuch exigencies where no Lawfull Miniſter is to be had, if upon hearty deſire of a ſociety of Chriſtians, it ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken by a <hi>Laick,</hi> the fact cannot be excuſed of the party, that ſhall proceed further then he hath warrant, in regard that in ſuch a caſe,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:115443:79"/>the <hi>religious deſire</hi> of the well-affected company will be more acceptable, then the thing done unlawfully. In civil matters will any Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or Corporation in Univerſities, or Townes, take his Suffrage for good, which intrudeth himſelfe to have an intereſt in that, to which he is not called? The caſe is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alike. When our Saviour was called to be an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor for diviſion of an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who made me a judge?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.14</note> Declaring thereby that no action, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially concerning Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, we muſt preſume to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, more then by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment in his Word, we have our commiſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether the Infants of Believing Parents are to be baptized?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. II.</note> 
                     <hi>in regard 'tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:115443:79"/>they are deſtitute of Faith, which is the neceſſary qualification of ſuch who are to he admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>It hath been the <hi>Custome of the Church</hi> in all ages (and not at all denied) no not by <hi>Pelagius</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">D.</note> who denied originall ſin) till theſe latter dayes) to admit the children of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving parents to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme, and that as a Right due unto them, by eſpeciall priviledg of birth, within the boſom of Holy Church. Wherein the Church may be ſaid not only to have the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt to lead her thereunto, <hi>who commanded little children ſhould be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to come unto him, &amp; laid his hands upon them, the Kingdome of Heaven conſist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:115443:80"/>of ſuch.</hi> Mat. 19.14, 15. But likewiſe was warranted by that inference of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>if the root be Holy, the branches are alſo Holy.</hi> Rom. 11.16. Which though it be immediately ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Jews, and their off ſpring,</hi> yet by a parity of reaſon may be accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Christians, and their Children.</hi> An <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Sanctity</hi> being to be found in theſe, as wel as the other, whereby they have a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent intereſt, and right to thoſe means, by which the ordinance of Chriſt is, his Church ſhould be Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Neither may the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Childes</hi> incapacity to believe, or underſtand the nature of the Baptiſmall vow be any bar for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion thereunto, more then the ſame incapacity in
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:115443:80"/>the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> was an obſtacle to his circumciſion: who it is preſumeable, at eight dayes old could then under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand no more of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, of which Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was the Signe, then the Chriſtian infant now can of the promiſe, and vow made by him in Baptiſm; and yet was he commanded to be circumciſed under paine of exciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14. Add to this that infants, as well as men, were admitted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into covenant with the Lord under the <hi>Law.</hi> Deut. 29.10, 11, 12. And why by the ſame reaſon ſhould they not enjoy that priviledg un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Goſpell?</hi> and ſo Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme the Sacrament there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The Covenant of the one being as ample, and of as large extent as the other. For which we have the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:115443:81"/>judgment of Saint Peter, Act. 2.38.39. We ſhall find therefore the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of infants</hi> continued all along in the Church in an uninterrupted line. Which cuſtome of theirs certainly was derived from the <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Apoſtles</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if we wil give any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to the authority of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen, St. Auſtin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſiae ab Apoſtolis traditionem accepi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am parvulis dare bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmum, in <hi>Rom. c. 6.</hi>
                     </note> and others of the <hi>Fathers:</hi> or have any regard or conſideration that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves did baptize whole houſes; in which it is to be conceived there were ſome children,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus l. <hi>1.</hi> de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. merit. c. <hi>16.</hi> dicit, traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem bane a Domino per Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> as well as thoſe of riper yeers. And with ſmall force of argument may that of Mat. 28.19. <hi>Go teach all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Baptizing them</hi> &amp;c. make this to ſignify nothing, if it be remembered that the word in the originall (in our
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:115443:81"/>tranſlation tendred <hi>to teach</hi>) is properly, and according to the genuine ſignification thereof <hi>to make Diſciples,</hi> or receive into Diſcipleſhip all nations, &amp;c. of which <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> is the <hi>ceremony;</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sacrament of our initiation, or admittance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the School of Chriſt: and of this infants are as capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as thoſe more growne in yeers. <hi>To make a diſciple</hi> not denoting that any one cometh ſuch to the School of Chriſt, but what after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he becometh by Chriſtian inſtitution. Of which thing the Church hath been very carefull, providing for them <hi>Sponſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> who are not only <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> of the promiſe, and ſolemne vow made by them in baptiſm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> for them alſo; and in
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:115443:82"/>caſe of the death, or neglect of their parents, when they come to age, are bound to ſee them Chriſtianly edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the obligation entred into by them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether Baptiſme be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſalvation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. III.</note> 
                     <hi>that all dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without it, even infants are damned? and what is to be thought of thoſe perſons, through whoſe default, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are deprived thereof, &amp; dye not having received it?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>That <hi>regeneration</hi> is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation, or Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, doth manifeſtly appear, by what our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our taught <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> Jo. 3.3. of which as the <hi>Spirit</hi> is the neceſſary inward cauſe, ſo <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary outward mean there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. v. 5. Hence God is ſaid with <hi>water to ſanctifie,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:115443:82"/>and cleanſe his Church.</hi> Epheſ.5.26. <hi>Saint Paul</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it the balne. or <hi>font of regeneration.</hi> Tit. 3.5. And <hi>Saint Peter</hi> adviſeth men to receive it, as an outward effectuall meanes, <hi>for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſins, Act.</hi> 2.38. Upon this ground many of the <hi>Fathers</hi> judge very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely concerning ſuch, who have died unbaptized, eſpecially Infants; towards which, there is none more rigid, then Saint <hi>Austin:</hi> who is therefore ſtyled, <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus pater infantum.</hi> Yet the <hi>Church</hi> herein hath ſhewed her ſelfe a more <hi>indulgent mother,</hi> and hath mingled her Judgement with Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, having conſtantly held, that as the <hi>wilful neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,</hi> or contempt thereof, is a ſin of a very high nature, and damnable, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:115443:83"/>from the puniſhment to be inflicted upon the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14. <hi>That ſoul ſhall be cut off from among his people,</hi> ſo the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation thereof,</hi> where there is an impoſſibility of having it, hath been ſupplied to ſuch believers, as have been of judgement by their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement deſire of it, and to Infants by the ſecret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of others. God having not tyed his grace abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to baptiſme. Beſide, ſuch is his lenity, that unto things altogether impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he bindeth none, and if we cannot performe what is commanded us, accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the will for the deed: or where that is wanting, by reaſon of their age, doth otherwiſe diſpenſe with his ordinance, by the ſecret wayes of his owne incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:115443:83"/>mercy. But notwithſtanding this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth not any from guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of blood, whoſe ſcrupulous curioſity ſhould cauſe an ordinance of ſo high a concernment as this, to be withheld, <hi>wherein our mercileſſe ſtrictneſſe</hi> (ſaith a learned Author) <hi>may be our own harm, not theirs towards whom we ſhew it, and we for the hardneſſe of our hearts may periſh, albeit they through Gods unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mercy may live.</hi> An e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent example to this purpoſe, we have in <hi>Moſes:</hi> whoſe neglect to circumciſe his Son, drew a judgement upon himſelfe: as the like neglect in us to baptize our Infants, may kindle Gods wrath againſt us, and that deſervedly, if we conſider the multitude of ſouls, that
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:115443:84"/>by this meanes may be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded, ſhould we ſuffer them to run on, till they come to ripeneſſe of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; that ſo they may be converted, and then bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, as Infidels heretofore have been, a cunning arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Satan to deſtroy Chriſtianity, by making it a ſinne to engage any early to the ſervice of Chriſt. Wherein the Prince of this world hath managed his buſineſſe with as much ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, as when he ſet <hi>Julian</hi> on work to plunder the Church of their revenue: both equally tending to the deſtruction of Chriſtian Religion, the one <hi>cutting off the branches,</hi> as the other did <hi>hew up the root.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether the</hi> ſigne of the Croſſe,<note place="margin">C. IV.</note> 
                     <hi>according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in our Liturgy, may be
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:115443:84"/>lawfully uſed in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Baptiſm?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Not onely to the Jew is the Croſſe of Chriſt an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,<note place="margin">D.</note> but we have thoſe, who though nothing can ſeem more odions unto them, then to be ſaid to put Chriſt to death, yet crucifie his members, in revilings, and diſgraces: and amongſt other reaſons they pretend, this is not the leaſt, becauſe they are for the Croſſe in Baptiſme, and defend the Liturgy in the lawfull uſe thereof. But to paſſe by theſe Sons of thunder. Thoſe that are more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate will reſt themſelves ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by our Church-book, why that ceremony is uſed, as alſo for the lawfulneſſe thereof: if they will allow the Church what St. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <pb n="156" facs="tcp:115443:85"/>giveth to her, a power to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act laws concerning <hi>decency and order:</hi> and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider too, that it hath been a laudable rite, and very antient in the Church of Chriſt, taken up in defiance of the Pagans, to tell them wherein the <hi>glory of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians</hi> did conſiſt, even in the <hi>Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> which by them was accompted the ſhame and diſgrace of their profeſſion. And though it may be objected now, that the cauſe being taken away, 'twill be uſeleſs if not ſuperſtitious to keep it on foot ſtill; yet may ſuch remember, 1. that all things, whoſe uſe doth ceaſe, are not preſently to be taken away, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: witneſſe the <hi>brazen Serpent,</hi> which was reſerved till the dayes of <hi>Ezechia,</hi>
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:115443:85"/>as a <hi>monument of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> to which purpoſe alſo the <hi>pot of Mannah,</hi> and the <hi>rod of Aa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. 2. Though we have not Pagans to deale with, yet 'tis to be feared there are too many, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe who take upon them the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, who though they will not endure to be called enemies, yet are <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of the Croſſe of Chriſt.</hi> 3. That it doth ſerve us as a <hi>memoriall,</hi> to put us in minde of our duty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Neither can it weigh with any rationall man, what is buzzed in the ears of men to amuſe them, that it is an Idol, and hath been abuſed to Idolatry, in which charge the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Croſſe is concerned, not <hi>ours.</hi> 'Twill be no good
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:115443:86"/>reaſon, becauſe the Papiſts have abuſed the Croſſe to Superſtition, therefore we ſhould be denied the lawful uſe thereof. Beſide the <hi>Sun, and the Moon</hi> were worſhiped by the <hi>Heathen, Paul and Barnabas,</hi> deified by the men of <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> the <hi>bread in the Sacrament</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> yet I hope upon this bottom, none will be ſo indiſcreet, as to adjudge them to eternall deſtruction. Neither can they be led thereunto from that <hi>inſtance</hi> (ſo much uſed) of the <hi>Brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> whence it may onely be inferred, that the <hi>ſame individuall thing idolized,</hi> is to be deſtroyed, but not their <hi>whole kind.</hi> We may not burne all trees, becauſe one tree, or grove hath been abuſed to Idolatry.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:115443:86"/>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>What is to be done,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. V.</note> 
                     <hi>that one may worthily receive the Lords Supper?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Obſerve that rule of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">D.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>But let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of that bread, and drink of that cup.</hi> To doe which rightly, it is requiſite he make a twofold inquiry into himſelf, 1. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his <hi>Faith,</hi> 2. his <hi>manners.</hi> 1. For his <hi>Faith,</hi> that he hath a competent, and right underſtanding of the principles in Religion, particularly concerning the doctrine of the Sacraments, ſo as to be able to render ſome account thereof, as alſo <hi>to diſcerne the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> which laſt, upon no terms, he can be ſaid to doe, who maketh his approach to this Holy Table, with no other devotion, then if he
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:115443:87"/>came to ſit down at a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon repaſt, the <hi>vice</hi> not onely <hi>taxed,</hi> but <hi>puniſhed</hi> in the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> To ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Conſcience therefore in this particular, let him remember,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.29.</note> 1. it is <hi>the Lords body,</hi> he is invited to a moſt high, and myſterious mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; yet ſuch is the love of Chriſt to him, that he is permitted, not only <hi>to look</hi> thereinto, but to partake thereof. 2. He <hi>prophane it not</hi> as the Corinthians did with their owne Feaſts, ſo with <hi>irreverence, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. 3.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31.</note> He judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe moſt unworthy of ſo high an entertainment, and favour a ſinner the chiefeſt of ſinners. Now II. for his <hi>manners,</hi> he is to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry whether he hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, according to the <hi>rules and doctrine of the Faith</hi> he
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:115443:87"/>profeſſeth, to which there is required, though not <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act,</hi> yet ſincere obedience.</hi> If in either of theſe he <hi>prove,</hi> and not <hi>approve</hi> of himſelf, he ought to abſtaine from thoſe holy myſteries, till ſuch time he hath either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his knowledg, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his manners, at leaſt in a reſolution, and ſerious purpoſe of Holy living. For as to be qualified to receive this Sacrament worthily, <hi>knowledge</hi> is neceſſary to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the head,</hi> ſo likewiſe is repentance to purifie the <hi>heart,</hi> both which muſt be rightly prepared for this work. Neither the <hi>ignorant,</hi> nor the <hi>unholy</hi> perſon being fit gueſts to ſup with Chriſt. But yet there is one more beſide our ſelves, concerned in this worke, which is our neighbour, towards whom
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:115443:88"/>we muſt he affected with Charity, which is the <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol,</hi> or badge of a Diſciple of Chriſt, and is the <hi>cement</hi> to ioyne, and knit the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants together: whence the Sacrament may in a moſt ſweet, and genuine ſenſe be termed a <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> without it being ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>diſunion,</hi> then ſo to be called. Indeed this is the <hi>ſalt of the Sacrifice,</hi> without the which nothing is to be offered, as well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, as the Law.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether any one who hath a ſuit at Law with his neighbor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. VI.</note> 
                     <hi>or is at private difference with him, may with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience come to the L: Table?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>As to <hi>private differences,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">D.</note> the caſe is quickly reſolved. It being manifeſt that this <hi>Holy Feaſt</hi> was inſtituted by our Saviour, not only to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:115443:88"/>
                     <hi>ſhew forth his death,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be a <hi>Signe,</hi> and <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol of Love,</hi> with which they ought to embrace each other, that doe partake thereof: 1 Cor. 10.17. And as a commentary to this Text you have the Practiſe of the Chriſtians in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, who before they received the Euchariſt, did greet one another with an <hi>Holy Kiſſe,</hi> to ſignify not only their <hi>Communion</hi> in faith, but <hi>union</hi> in heart likewiſe; and therefore im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after it was cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated began their <hi>agapae,</hi> or love Feaſts. None therefore are to adventure to offer <hi>Their gift on this Altar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5.23.24.</note> whoſe hearts are enflamed with anger, or revenge A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Brother: but there muſt be an atonement made with him firſt, that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:115443:89"/>ſo God may be atoned, and the Sacrifice accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For in vaine doe they beg a boone from the all-merciful Lord, whoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs hearts are hardened againſt their fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. Wherefore all, who expect welcome, here, muſt lay aſide their anger, &amp; come in peace, and love. But though God is pleaſed thus to pluck the <hi>Sword of revenge</hi> out of the hand of each <hi>private perſon,</hi> yet does he eſtabliſh it in the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi> For (ſaith <hi>Saint Paul</hi>) <hi>he beareth not the Sword in vaine, for he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evill.</hi> Rom. 13.4. Contrary to the calumnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Julian the Apoſtate;</hi> who upon this pretext, that Chriſtian religion did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:115443:89"/>revenge, did therefore impugne it, as deſtructive to all government: When it is manifeſt Chriſts Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine aboliſhed not, but did vindicate it rather, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting every private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to uſurpe the Supream authority, or ſit in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall throne. To decide the firſt branch of the caſe therefore, we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and take notice of three things. 1. That <hi>judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Proceedings at law</hi> are not forbidden in the new Teſtament, but the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry warranted, as may moſt evidently appear, not only from expreſſe texts of Scripture, Rom. 13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. But likewiſe from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Saint Paul.</hi> Our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> not refuſing to anſwer at the tribunall of <hi>Pilat,</hi> and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:115443:90"/>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf appealing to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Whence it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that a ſute at law with ones neighbour, is no ſufficient plea for a man to abſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Yet 2. there ought to be labour, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection that we our ſelves add not <hi>fewell</hi> to enflame this publick controverſy, or deny ſuch juſt meanes to quench it, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to bring things to an accord, whereby amity may be eſtabliſhed: or contend concerning trifles, and things of no value. They who are conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they are pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant in any of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, are not clad with the <hi>Wedding Garment of love,</hi> and ſo cannot hope for any kind reception at the hands of Chriſt in this great ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:115443:90"/>To which purpoſe it is deſired of them, they ſhould take a view of theſe places in Scripture, Rom. 12.18. <hi>If it be poſsible, as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men,</hi> Ro. 14.19. <hi>Let us therefore follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith one may edifie another.</hi> 1 Cor. 6.7. <hi>Now therefore there it utterly a fault among you; becauſe ye goe to law one with another. Why doe ye not rather take wrong? Why doe ye not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer your ſelves to be defrauded?</hi> 3. We are to take care, we doe not ſeeke for <hi>juſtice</hi> at the hand of the Magiſtrate; that ſo under that pretext, we may <hi>cloake,</hi> and <hi>exerciſe our malice</hi> the more freely, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our neighbour. This
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:115443:91"/>is but to <hi>clothe private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge in a publick dreſſe,</hi> and to make it ſo much the <hi>more odius to God,</hi> as it is <hi>gilded over with hypocriſie.</hi> Therefore remember it is the voice off God that ſpeaks unto thee, Lev. 19.18. <hi>Thou ſhalt not avenge, nor bear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grudg againſt the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of thy people, but thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf. I am the Lord.</hi> And that the ſame ſpirit, who denyeth thee not a lawfull proſecution of thy right, yet is ſo far from tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting revenge in thee that he commandeth thee to <hi>feed thine enemy</hi> when hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and if thirſty <hi>to give him drinke.</hi> Rom. 12.20.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether</hi> kneeling,<note place="margin">C. VII.</note> 
                     <hi>at the receiving of the Sacrament, be not a moſt</hi> pious, <hi>and</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>geſture?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:115443:91"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Were there nothing to commend this ceremony, in this high ſervice of religion, but the humility of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, certeinly it muſt needs be kindly enterteyned by that ſoule, where <hi>piety and devotion</hi> dwell, conſidering that the moſt High ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h not only a reſpect to the <hi>humble</hi> heart, but is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe well-pleaſed with ſuch <hi>externall behaviour,</hi> as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth beſt to teſtifie the ſame; but when to this, it is added, that it is the moſt <hi>ſignificant ſigne</hi> of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence which the creature ought to exhibite to God in <hi>ſupplication,</hi> and that, as the Sacrament is particularly delivered to every man therewith, ſo each man is bound to particularize, and apply to himſelf the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall benefit by devout
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:115443:92"/>invocation of Gods name, who then can be offended with our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning the decent uſe of it? Or queſtion his <hi>piety,</hi> who in obedience thereunto ſhall obſerve it? I know it hath been, and is the fancy of ſome, that <hi>ſitting</hi> is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture better agreeing with the nature of a <hi>Supper;</hi> but ſuch ought to remember that it is no ordinary meale, but a <hi>heavenly banquet</hi> to which we are invited, <hi>in which Chriſt with all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits is exhibited to us,</hi> and therefore ſuch an <hi>humble</hi> poſture of body would beſt become us, as did ſerve beſt to expreſſe reverence, and devotion at ſo high, and holy a myſtery. Neither will it be any prejudice thereunto, to quarrell at this geſture, becauſe Chriſt
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:115443:92"/>did not uſe it when he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred the Sacrament to his Apoſtles, as neither did he <hi>ſitting,</hi> but <hi>lying on a bed,</hi> according to the cuſtome of thoſe Eaſterne nations. In theſe circumſtances not preſcribing their manner, but leaving the determination of them to the <hi>prudence</hi> and <hi>judgement</hi> of thoſe, who are to ſee them done <hi>decently,</hi> and <hi>in order.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115443:93"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:93"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>ABſolution of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, more then petitory. <hi>Pag. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Agapae</hi> uſed at the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the reaſon, <hi>Pag. 163</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> why read in the Church <hi>Pag. 37</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>Baptiſme, whether neceſſary to Salvation, <hi>150.</hi> the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of thoſe, through whoſe default Infants are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thereof. <hi>Pag. 151</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>Charity to our neighbour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a Communicant. <hi>Pag. 159</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:115443:94"/>
               <item>Chriſtian Religion, whether a politick invention only. <hi>Pag. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why to be preferred before other Religions. <hi>Pag. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whether to be enforced. <hi>17</hi> not deſtructive to Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. <hi>Pag. 167</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Christ, whether to be called the Son of the Father, or Holy Ghost, <hi>46.</hi> whether he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended into Hell. <hi>Pag. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſcience what it is. <hi>1.</hi> The rules for it to walk by. <hi>6.</hi> The praejudice, by neglect of them. <hi>Pag. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Content in what eſtate, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoever enjoyned in the laſt Commandement. <hi>Pag. 113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Covenant old and new, the difference betwixt them. <hi>Pag. 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Commandements. Caſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them. <hi>63.</hi> How divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>64.</hi> Whether to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Chriſtians. <hi>Pag. 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Creed, Caſes concerning it. <hi>41.</hi> Whether compoſed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.
<pb facs="tcp:115443:94"/>
                  <hi>44.</hi> Perill of reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. <hi>42.</hi> Whether a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſummary of Faith. <hi>Pag. 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Other points how to be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to it. <hi>pag. 60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Croſſe, whether it may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſed in Baptiſme. <hi>pag. 154.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Objections to the contrary anſwered. <hi>pag. 156</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>Dancing of men with women, whether lawfull. <hi>pag. 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Debts their kindes, <hi>130.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ſued for. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Debtors that are careleſs, their danger. <hi>pag. 104</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>Examination required before receiving the Lords Supper. <hi>159.</hi> The manner in which we are to proceed. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>Faith, the nature of it that justifieth. <hi>pag. 66</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>God, whence inferred. <hi>pag. 12</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:95"/>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>Hallowing Gods name, what it is. <hi>pag. 124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Holy dayes, whether to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>pag. 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Holy Ghoſt, what warrant we have to direct our prayers to him. <hi>pag. 118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Holy kiſſe, when uſed, and the reaſon. <hi>pag. 163</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>Images whether to be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to remaine in Churches, their uſe, their abuſe. <hi>pag. 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Infants of believing parents, whether to be baptized. <hi>pag. 144</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Irreverence in receiving the Myſteries, the danger of it. <hi>pag. 159</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>Kneeling at the receiving of the Sacrament, whether a pious and decent gesture. <hi>pag. 168</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>Lay-Impropriators, whether with Conſcience they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the right from the
<pb facs="tcp:115443:95"/>Church. <hi>pag. 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Letter, whether to be laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, that the ſpirit may act the more freely. <hi>pag 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lying, whether upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text lawfull. <hi>pag. 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lords Prayer, caſes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it. <hi>pag. 116</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>Marriages within degrees of conſanguinity, or affinity, or after ſeparation for fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether lawfull. <hi>pag. 95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Murder of a mans ſelf, whether juſtifiable. <hi>pag. 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Merchants, whether they may over-reach. <hi>pag. 104</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N.</head>
               <item>Name of God, what it import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>pag. 123</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>Oath what it is, whether to be diſpenſed with, the difference of it from an aſſeveration. <hi>pag. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ordinaries, whether to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded. <hi>pag. 126</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:96"/>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>Painting, patching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be approved. <hi>pag. 98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Perjury, whether to be excuſed upon any pretext. <hi>pag. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Petition the ſixth, the extent thereof. <hi>pag. 137</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Polygamy whether lawful. <hi>pag. 96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poſſeſſed, the courſe to be taken with them. <hi>pag. 137</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prayer, whether to be made for all without exception. <hi>pag. 118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proteſtants, whether by depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from Popery, they ſet up a new Religion. <hi>16.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a ſafe conſcience they may be preſent at the Maſſe. <hi>pag. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Puniſhments proportioned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to demerits. <hi>pag. 15.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>Religion, Caſes concerning it, <hi>12.</hi> Not to be planted by the Sword, but by the Word. <hi>pag. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Roman Church, whether the Catholick. <hi>pag. 52</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:96"/>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>Sacraments, their nature. <hi>140.</hi> Whether adminiſtred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a lawfull Miniſter, there be a nullity in the action. <hi>pag. 141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Salvation whether to be had without Chriſt. <hi>pag. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Scripture, caſes concerning it. <hi>25.</hi> How to be aſſured it is the Word of God. <hi>ibid.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appointed to be a rule. <hi>27.</hi> The method obſerved in it. <hi>ibid.</hi> Why ſome parts of it not appointed to be read. <hi>pag. 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whether to be uſed in charms, <hi>&amp;c. pag. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Son, what warrant to direct our prayers to him. <hi>pag. 119</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, what it is, <hi>ibid.</hi> Whether all are forgiven. <hi>pag. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sunday, whether to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. <hi>pag. 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Subjects, whether they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb facs="tcp:115443:97"/>the ſupream Magiſtrate. <hi>pag. 87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Stage-playes, whether law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>pag. 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Supper of the Lord, how one may worthily receive it. <hi>139.</hi> Whether one at Law with his neighbour, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate difference with him, may come with a ſafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thither. <hi>pag. 162</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>Tentations from God &amp; Satan, how to be diſtinguiſhed, <hi>pag. 133</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tradeſmen, whether they may over-reach by falſe weights, or other deceit, <hi>pag. 164</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>Vowes Monasticall, whether lawfull. <hi>pag. 23</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>Word read, whether of power to beget Faith. <hi>pag. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>World testifieth there is a God <hi>pag. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wizards, whether to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with. <hi>pag. 125</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115443:97"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
